<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pearle of practise, or Practisers pearle, for phisicke and chirurgerie. Found out by I. H. (a spagericke or distiller) amongst the learned obseruations and prooued practises of many expert men in both faculties. Since his death it is garnished and brought into some methode by a welwiller of his</title>
            <author>Hester, John, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118051</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853260</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18630</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18630)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1242:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pearle of practise, or Practisers pearle, for phisicke and chirurgerie. Found out by I. H. (a spagericke or distiller) amongst the learned obseruations and prooued practises of many expert men in both faculties. Since his death it is garnished and brought into some methode by a welwiller of his</title>
                  <author>Hester, John, d. 1593.</author>
                  <author>Fourestier, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 63, 68-83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field, dwelling in the Black-friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.H. = John Hester.</note>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Iames Fourestier.</note>
                  <note>Pages 64-67 missing in number only; text unaffected.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PEARLE OF PRACTISE, <hi>OR</hi> PRACTISERS PEARLE, FOR PHISICKE AND CHIRVRGERIE.</p>
            <p>Found out by <hi>I. H.</hi> (a <hi>Spagericke</hi> or diſtiller) amongſt the learned obſeruations and prooued practiſes of many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert men in both faculties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since his death it is garniſhed and brought into ſome methode by a welwiller of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Field,</hi> dwelling in the Black-friers. 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:2"/>
            <head>TO THE FAMOVS MECAENAS, OF ALL GOOD LEARNING, HIS HONORABLE GOOD PATRONE, SIR GEORGE CAREY, Knight, Knight Mareſchall of her Maieſties houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Gouernour of the Iſle of Wight, &amp;c. Health of ſoule and bodie, be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied for euer and euer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His peece of timber, which an other man had roughly hewen ouer, wanting a name (which I haue giuen vnto it) but not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence &amp; patronage, vnder whoſe couert, it may be ſhielded, from the venemous darts of carping toungs: thinke it not amiſſe, to preſent the ſame vnto your excellent worthineſſe; ſith you haue euen borne, as good and liberall a minde, to learning, and learned workemen, in any facultie, as any noble Gentleman throughout this Realme of England. The ſubiect matter, whereon it conſiſteth, is charitable learning or learned charitie, practiſed vpon and performed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe, which haue ſtood in neede: and publiſhed by thoſe, that are not aſhamed, to ſhew their names (though for good cauſes two letters may yet ſerue to expreſſe them) being well knowne to the beſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:18630:3"/>
may be compared with the beſt, in the facultie of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and keeping of a good conſcience. The ground the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being firme, and the title free hold, whereupon the frame ſtandeth: how can the ſtormie windes, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the mouthes, of vnwholeſome Aeoles, infect it with their corruption, or one whit moue it with all their violence? I learned this true poſition long ago amongſt other axiomes in the nurſerie at Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge. <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſumus, &amp;c.</hi> we are not borne for our ſelues alone, but our countrie challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth an intereſt in vs, our children, our frendes, and our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, do laye claime to vs. Howbeit ſuch wicked dayes are come vpon vs, though a man, for glorie to God, loue to his poſteritie, good will to his countrie, or other honeſt motiues, makes priuate things pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, for the common commoditie, of the Church and common wealth; he is not prayſed of any, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of many, and condemned of all malitious Momes. <hi>Bonum quo communius eo melius,</hi> hath bene and will be a true morall principle: though ſome great learned men do ſcorne to put it in execution. The beſt Maiſter that euer I ſerued did reproue and condemne him, for an euill and vngratious ſeruant, that hid his talent in a napkin, refuſing to put it forth, to his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters aduantage: <hi>Bind him hand and foote, and caſt him into vtter darkneſſe</hi> was, and will be the guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, of ſuch priuate companions. As thoſe practiſers, are iuſtly reproued, which (to toll in more cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers) do hang out their ſignes, and gild their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, profeſſing much cunning, and haue little or no learning: ſo dare I not auouch, to be of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which purpoſe nothing leſſe, then to practiſe
<pb facs="tcp:18630:3"/>
their cunning. God gaue <hi>Galene</hi> leaue (as <hi>Sippontinus</hi> writeth) to liue ſeuen ſcore yeares, what ſeparation he made of impurities from any ſimple, or what parting of elementes he vſed, I could neuer yet read or heare. But <hi>Paracelſus</hi> (nicknamed the Sectarie) did more good in three ſcore yeares by working with his owne handes (according to natures direction) concealing no Theorie nor practiſe from poſteritie, ſhewing much art, <hi>celando artem,</hi> though <hi>Filijs artis</hi> he is as playne as a pathway. His ſchollers and followers, that practiſed his teaching, and taught his practiſing, are a cloud of witneſſes, to make demonſtration of this true poſition. That with a few medecines, rightly compounded, and with ſome ſimples ſimplie, and without couin prepared, more good hath bene, and may be done, in one weeke againſt any diſeaſe, then in a moneth with all the groſſe confections (as <hi>VVecker</hi> termes them) in their blew pots, or with their hoarie heared drugs, in their braue boxes, which once in a yeare or two (if all men deale truly) muſt be ſwept out of dores. Shew me not the meate, but ſhew me the man: talke not of the receit, but ſpeake truly of the effect. So many as are ſand blind, and will not be ſtone blind, may verifie the truth of the ſafeſt kinde of curation; if they will beſtow the paynes, to peruſe the booke following. Herein is no bragging of cures done, nor promiſe of impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities: but the manner how, the perſons who, and vpon whom they were performed, is truly and playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe, euen as they were deliuered by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or word of mouth. Briefly and in a word to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I appeale vnto their conſciences that haue
<pb facs="tcp:18630:4"/>
found certaintie in this kinde of courſe, for all deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diſeaſes: albeit they will not be perſwaded to giue euery one his due, but ſpeake worſe of <hi>Spagirickes,</hi> then they haue founde by them. Thus not to be further te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious vnto your Worſhip, I do breake off in the halfe way, not doubting, of your fauorable acceptation of this poore gift, which I beſeech your noble eyes, not ſo much to regard, as the true &amp; ſeruiceable hart of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, to pray for your felicitie, for my good Ladies hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, the health and proſperitie of all your retinew.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in the poſsible performance of all kind of dutie for your ſelfe or your houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, To command at all times, <hi>Iames Foureſtier.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:4"/>
            <head>TO THE FRENDLY READER, AS MVCH HEALTH AS HE WISHETH OF SOVLE AND BODY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>En many times meddle in ſome matters, wherein they take more toile then thanke for their labors: and he which thinkes in the night, that he hath pleaſed all, ſhall find in the morning, that he hath angred ſome. So many as know me well, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I was chiefly addicted, within theſe eight or nine yeares, that is vnto the studie and practiſe of the ſoule Phiſicke; may now make a queſtion, of my medling ſo long vvith bodily Phiſicke. But my two fold anſwer they may take with them, for their ſatisfaction. Firſt that I keepe ſtill <hi>Depoſitum illud,</hi> vvhich God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto me (and ſealed the ſame, by mine own ſpirituall birth, and other mens ſanctification) till he that hath ſaid, Go, points the time, and giues the occaſion, of my further ſeruice, in that waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie function. Secondly, as vvhen I conuerſed in that calling, I vvas chargeable to none: ſo (not ſurceaſing the ſame of mine owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord) I haue ſince by God his bleſſing of my labors herein, as not greatly inriched my ſelf: ſo not impoueriſhed any. That vvherein I haue thus continued, ſith it concerneth learning, and an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s maintenance, cannot or ought not offend any, that are well in their vvits. Theſe few ſecrets, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in this Collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix thereto adioyning (which I haue reduced into methode for his ſake that gathered them here and there) cannot or ought not to ſcandalize any, that haue a ſanctified cunning, in Phiſicke or Chirurgerie. I muſt needes tell thee, that I leane more to that ſafe, ſpeedy, and pleaſant kind of curation with medecines rightly prepared, then to the careleſſe compoſition, made by addition of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimples, clogged with more impurities, then are in that ſimple, which they labour to correct. I dare alſo auouch, that any poore body, may better commit his craſie body, to be healed or helped, of any outward or inward maladie, by the right prepared medecines, for the value of ten ſhillings (which he can hardly spare) then a wealthy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to their deceits) I would ſay receits) for ten crownes,
<pb facs="tcp:18630:5"/>
which he may well inough forbeare: Many of the ignorant ſort haue counted the chymicall or <hi>Paracelſicall</hi> Phiſicke dangerous, and not without cauſe, for wofull experience hath brought it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſuſpition. But (good Reader) heare me in that which He tell thee, and ſo take thine anſwere for this time. Some of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and moſt of the ignorant, haue in generall despiſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by your leaue after they haue heard in particular of the excellent ſucceſſe attained by many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they haue aduentured vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe, without knowledge, experience, direction: and ſo haue made many patients to ſmart for it. Therfore I would not that the fine finge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Phiſitian ſhould ſcorne to weare this pearle, which is as fit for Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> Lack-latin, for the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleaper, or cogging quackeſaluer, as a pipe for an aſſe, or a cage for a cow. The ſalts, oyles, waters, extractes, tinctures, ſimples prepared, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſimples co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned mentioned in this booke or not mentioned, I meane not to make ſale of (as the Grocer doth or the Apothecary:) but I keepe them in ſtore, and meane to increaſe them, for mine owne vſe, and my frends, and for ſuch as ſhall need the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the learned counſell, of Phiſicke rules, ſhall giue occaſion. The greateſt part of them, were prepared by <hi>Iohn Heſter</hi> of Paules wharfe, now deceaſed, a man that ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t much, &amp; inda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gered his body, about ſuch workes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many excellent men haue enioyed the benefite. The effect of his labour, hath and doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend him, in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, which haue theſe many yeares made proofe, of theſe his prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. All which as not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince I bought of the Suruiuer: ſo I am willing at all times, to part with any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſalue the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, or heale the diſeaſed. In the meane while and for euermore, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit thee (Gentle Reader) in health or in ſickneſſe, to the protection of the Arch-Phiſitian, and creator of our ſoules and bodies, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſerue vs, and all that be his, vnto the end and in the end.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudie in the Blackefriers <date>the <hi>19.</hi> of Ianuary.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy louing frend. <hi>Iames Foureſtier.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="lists_of_ingredients">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:5"/>
            <head>A NOTE OF SVCH PREPARED SIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and compoſitions, as are mentioned in this booke: with other things, not mentioned therein, whereof there is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular vſe in Phiſicke and Chirurgerie, and are to be had at the houſe of <hi>Iames Foureſtier</hi> aforeſayd.</head>
            <div n="salts" type="part">
               <head>The names of the ſeuerall kindes of Saltes.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Salts of Herbes as, of</head>
                  <item>VVOrmwood.</item>
                  <item>Mintes.</item>
                  <item>Carduus Benedictus.</item>
                  <item>Chamomill.</item>
                  <item>Radiſh.</item>
                  <item>S. Iohns wort.</item>
                  <item>Sea holy.</item>
                  <item>Centaurie.</item>
                  <item>Roſemarie.</item>
                  <item>Fennell.</item>
                  <item>Time.</item>
                  <item>Beane ſtalkes.</item>
                  <item>Blacke Hellebore.</item>
                  <item>Brionie.</item>
                  <item>Sage.</item>
                  <item>Maioram.</item>
                  <item>Germander.</item>
                  <item>Mehlote.</item>
                  <item>Chamepitis.</item>
                  <item>Hyſope.</item>
                  <item>Feuerfew.</item>
                  <item>Gentian.</item>
                  <item>Aliſanders.</item>
                  <item>Mugwort.</item>
                  <item>Fumitorie.</item>
                  <item>Origanum.</item>
                  <item>Eufraſie, or Eyebright.</item>
                  <item>Tartar Chriſtalline.</item>
                  <item>Pockwood, or <hi>Lignum vitae.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Saltes of trees and fruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call plants, as</head>
                  <item>ASh.</item>
                  <item>Iuniper.</item>
                  <item>Iuie.</item>
                  <item>Broome.</item>
                  <item>Vine.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Saltes of ſpices and other things, as of</head>
                  <item>CLoues.</item>
                  <item>Ginger.</item>
                  <item>Cinamon.</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs.</item>
                  <item>Vrine.</item>
                  <item>Armoniacke of Amber.</item>
                  <item>Vineger.</item>
                  <item>Salt, or Suger, of Saturne.</item>
                  <item>Salt niter out of Ireland.</item>
                  <item>Alome del Plume.</item>
                  <item>Tartar ſix times calcined.</item>
                  <item>Sal conditum.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lapilli Vrinae.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Salt common calcined.</item>
                  <item>A cauſticke.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18630:6"/>
                  <head>The names of the diuers kinds of vvaters as of</head>
                  <item>CInamon.</item>
                  <item>Cloues.</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs.</item>
                  <item>Franckincenſe.</item>
                  <item>Turpentine.</item>
                  <item>Waxe.</item>
                  <item>Honie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua fortis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua Regis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua Spermatis ranarum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Egges.</item>
                  <item>Harts horne.</item>
                  <item>Amber.</item>
                  <item>Vineger diſtilled.</item>
                  <item>Spirit of wine.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fragariae</hi> with ſpirite of wine.</item>
                  <item>Mans ſcull.</item>
                  <item>Pockwood.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reſinae pini.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Percepier.</item>
                  <item>Roſes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> of roſes.</item>
                  <item>Sweet water.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> of Percepier.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> of Iuniper berries.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> of Turkie balme.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aqua Benedicta.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Walnuts.</item>
                  <item>Anniſe ſeede.</item>
                  <item>Sal gumme.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="oils" type="part">
               <head>Oyles of Herbes as of</head>
               <list>
                  <head>The ſeuerall kindes of oyles drawen by diſtillation or otherwiſe prepared.</head>
                  <item>SWeet margerome.</item>
                  <item>Sage.</item>
                  <item>Time.</item>
                  <item>Origanum.</item>
                  <item>Roſemarie ſlowers.</item>
                  <item>Hyſope.</item>
                  <item>Mintes.</item>
                  <item>Lauender.</item>
                  <item>Penyroiall.</item>
                  <item>Camomill flowers.</item>
                  <item>Nenufar groſſely prepared.</item>
                  <item>Betonie and Camomill groſſely prepared.</item>
                  <item>Roſes by diſtillation.</item>
                  <item>Thorne apple.</item>
                  <item>Wormwood.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Oyles of ſeedes as of</head>
                  <item>ANiſe.</item>
                  <item>Fennell.</item>
                  <item>Dill.</item>
                  <item>Carui or Caraway.</item>
                  <item>Commin.</item>
                  <item>Muſtard.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:18630:7"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Oyles of fruites, berries and spices, as of</head>
                  <item>NVttes.</item>
                  <item>Figges.</item>
                  <item>Sweet almondes.</item>
                  <item>Orenge peeles.</item>
                  <item>Lemon peeles.</item>
                  <item>Bay berries.</item>
                  <item>Iuniper berries.</item>
                  <item>Miſſelto of apples.</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs.</item>
                  <item>Cinamon.</item>
                  <item>Ginger.</item>
                  <item>Cloues.</item>
                  <item>Maces.</item>
                  <item>Pepper.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Oyles of trees, or woods, of gummes, ſtones, and other things, as of</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>LIgnum vitae.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Aſhe.</item>
                  <item>Broome.</item>
                  <item>Waxe.</item>
                  <item>Honie.</item>
                  <item>Turpentine.</item>
                  <item>Tarre.</item>
                  <item>Franckincenſe.</item>
                  <item>Colophonie.</item>
                  <item>Galbanum.</item>
                  <item>Sagapenum.</item>
                  <item>Maſticke.</item>
                  <item>Labdanum.</item>
                  <item>Ammoniacke.</item>
                  <item>Amber.</item>
                  <item>Iet.</item>
                  <item>Benzoin.</item>
                  <item>Storax liquide.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caſtoreum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mans ſcull.</item>
                  <item>Butter.</item>
                  <item>Egges.</item>
                  <item>Tartar.</item>
                  <item>Stinking oyle of Tartar.</item>
                  <item>Vitrioll.</item>
                  <item>Sulfur.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petroleum de Lateribus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Deares ſuet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spermacaeti.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wormes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The ſeuerall kindes of Extractes of Eſſences, as of Herbes, rootes, &amp;c.</head>
                  <item>VVOrmwood.</item>
                  <item>Chamomil.</item>
                  <item>Sage.</item>
                  <item>Celandine.</item>
                  <item>Betonie.</item>
                  <item>Agrimonie.</item>
                  <item>Tanſie.</item>
                  <item>Horehound.</item>
                  <item>Eufraſie.</item>
                  <item>Marygold.</item>
                  <item>Fumitory.</item>
                  <item>Henbane.</item>
                  <item>Chamepitis.</item>
                  <item>Tormentill.</item>
                  <item>Philipendula.</item>
                  <item>Blacke Hellebore.</item>
                  <item>Ariſtolochie.</item>
                  <item>Gentian.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Angelica.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sauine.</item>
                  <item>Perwincle.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carduus Bened.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Feuerfew.</item>
                  <item>Percepier.</item>
                  <item>Rue.</item>
                  <item>Peonie.</item>
                  <item>Iuniper.</item>
                  <item>Broome flowers.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hermodactiles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sena.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Agaricke.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cnicus</hi> or baſtard. Saffron.</item>
                  <item>Rubarb.</item>
                  <item>Colocinthis.</item>
                  <item>Soldanella.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Laureola.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aloes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Polipodie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bruſcus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Centorie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Enula campana.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Melliſſa</hi> or Balme.</item>
                  <item>Ginger.</item>
                  <item>Muske.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Squilla.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sarcocolla.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cantarides.</item>
                  <item>Spicknard.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zedoaria.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pepper.</item>
                  <item>Orenge peeles.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_medicinal_formulae">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:8"/>
            <head>A NOTE OF THE DIVERS KINDS of compoſitions as followeth.</head>
            <list>
               <item>LAudanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anodinum.</item>
               <item>Panchimagogon.</item>
               <item>Amuletum Palmarij.</item>
               <item>Oleum benedictum.</item>
               <item>Oleum ſine Mumia Tartari.</item>
               <item>Oleum Heracl. Rulandi.</item>
               <item>Mumia vitrioli.</item>
               <item>Creta vitrioli.</item>
               <item>Crocus Martis.</item>
               <item>Balſamum ſulphuris.</item>
               <item>Flos ſulphuris.</item>
               <item>Oleum Camphorae.</item>
               <item>Eſſencia perlarum.</item>
               <item>Flores Antimonij.</item>
               <item>Mercurius Antimonij.</item>
               <item>Vitrum Antimonij.</item>
               <item>Turpetum minerale Quercetani.</item>
               <item>Turpetum Diaph.</item>
               <item>Sulphur vitriolatum.</item>
               <item>Mercurius ſublimatus.</item>
               <item>Mercurius precipitatus.</item>
               <item>Aqua Theriacalis.</item>
               <item>Calx teſtarum ouorum.</item>
               <item>Emplaſtrum Fodicationis.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gibſons balme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Petra Philoſophale noſtra.</item>
               <item>Pillulae Aquilone.</item>
               <item>Oleum Hypericonis compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum.</item>
               <item>Oleum Balſami.</item>
               <item>Aqua Balſami.</item>
               <item>Dia Aromatico.</item>
               <item>Electuario Angelica.</item>
               <item>Balſamum artificiale.</item>
               <item>Electuarium magiſtrale.</item>
               <item>Aqua preſeruans.</item>
               <item>Magno liquore.</item>
               <item>Cerotum magiſtrale.</item>
               <item>Oleum Philoſophorum de Terebinth. &amp; cera.</item>
               <item>Vnguentum ex Lytargirio.</item>
               <item>Aqua reale.</item>
               <item>Sirupo del Ebulo compoſit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent againſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vnguento magno.</item>
               <item>Pillulae contra morbum Gallicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>Cordiale roſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine ſulphure.</item>
               <item>Balſamus vrinae deſcriptione Willichij.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our ſolutiue liquor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oyle of Nicotian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Paracelſus <hi>his Vulnerarie oyle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Water for the eyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Water for pinne and web.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aqua Perſicariae.</item>
               <item>Vnguento nigro.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent to cauſe haire to grow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent to clenſe wounds.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent defenſatiue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent ſtomachall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent againſt aches and bruiſes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18630:8"/>
                  <hi>Extract againſt all obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Adeps vrſi.</item>
               <item>Medulla Mummiae.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our compoſition againſt the ſtrangurie, Iſchurie, or ſtone in the bladder, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Balſamum Tartari.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spirite of honie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spirite of Tartar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tincture of ſulphur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powder to mundifie vlcers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mater Balſami.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A compoſition againſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſcalding.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vigoes balme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aqua del petra Vegetab.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tinctures of Spices.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spiritus tartari cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colcothare rectificat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Another water for the eyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Syrupus ſpinae merulae.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cinamon water.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vnguent</hi> de Peto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mans bloud dried.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Craneum humanum <hi>calcined.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our compoſition againſt all feuers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the wormes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gumme of the roote and herbe Henbane.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18630:9"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF ALL THE PRINCIPALL matters contained in the Collection.</head>
            <list>
               <head>In the Proeme are contained theſe things.</head>
               <item>THe dutie of an expert Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian. pag. 1</item>
               <item>The generall cure of wounds. 1</item>
               <item>Why wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heale quickly. 2</item>
               <item>How to deale generally with wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in the head. ibidem</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Woundes.</head>
               <item>A Greeuous wound on the head cruel. 3</item>
               <item>A daungerous wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cured in fiue dayes. ibidem</item>
               <item>A wound on the eare. ibidem</item>
               <item>Woundes in the head with the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the ſcull. 4</item>
               <item>Concuſions in the head or elſe where. 5</item>
               <item>Contuſion qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly healed. ibidem</item>
               <item>Wound in the head with the ſcull fractured. ibidem</item>
               <item>To heale woundes ſpeedily. 6</item>
               <item>Woundes by ſhot or launce. ibid.</item>
               <item>A ſingular remedie for the ſpeedie healing of woundes. ibidem</item>
               <item>Wounded eye with a ſplinter. 7</item>
               <item>Puncture in the eye. ibidem</item>
               <item>Another cure done in like maner. 7</item>
               <item>A ſquatted hand healed. 8</item>
               <item>A punctured arme healed. ibidem</item>
               <item>Fiue wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in the breaſt healed. 8</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of ſores, vlcers, &amp;c. and their cure.</head>
               <item>SOre mouthes healed. 9</item>
               <item>Vlcer in the vpper lippe. ibidem</item>
               <item>Vlcer in the throate. 10</item>
               <item>Scald head healed. ibidem</item>
               <item>Another for the ſame, ibidem</item>
               <item>Vlcer on the thombe. ibidem</item>
               <item>Vlcerated legge. 11</item>
               <item>Two putrified vlcers on the legge healed. ibidem</item>
               <item>Three vlcers in the legge healed. ib</item>
               <item>Old rotten ſores cured. 12</item>
               <item>Vlcers in moſt partes of the bodie and head. ibidem</item>
               <item>Scabs like the leproſie. 13</item>
               <item>A child healed that had the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch pockes. 14</item>
               <item>A canker cured. ibidem</item>
               <item>Pockie puſtules with Serpigo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. ibidem</item>
               <item>Tetters and ringwormes. 15</item>
               <item>Another. ibidem</item>
               <item>Tetters on womens breaſts. 16</item>
               <item>Shingles healed. ibidem</item>
               <item>To breake a plague ſore. ibidem</item>
               <item>Scabs and itch, &amp;c. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Three deepe fiſtulaes in the breaſt cured. ibidem</item>
               <item>Lichen or Impetigo cured. 18</item>
               <item>A great wenne taken away.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd part of the Collection.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Of the cures of internall diſeaſes.</head>
                  <item>OF greeuous aches and paine in the bodie. 19</item>
                  <item>Aches comming of the pockes cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. ibidem</item>
                  <item>An excellent vnguent to eaſe any payne. 20</item>
                  <item>To eaſe the gout. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To cure aches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of heate. 21</item>
                  <item>The cure of the ſcuruie. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Tumors throughout the body cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 22</item>
                  <item>Swelling of the cods. 23</item>
                  <item>Another of the ſame. ibidem</item>
                  <item>The Iſchiatica cured. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Againſt the crampe. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Againſt contraction of ſinewes. 24</item>
                  <item>A wrie necke ſet ſtraight. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. 25</item>
                  <item>Squinancie cured. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Alopecia cured. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To purge the head. ibidem</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18630:6"/>
                  <item>Pinne and web cured. 26</item>
                  <item>An approued water for the eyes. ib.</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To ſtay bleeding at the noſe. 27</item>
                  <item>Another for the ſame. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. 28</item>
                  <item>Other wayes to do the ſame. ibid.</item>
                  <item>Spatting of bloud. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Lift vp the vuula. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Cure of the hicket. 29</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>The falling ſickneſſe cured. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Iaundies cured. 30</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. 31</item>
                  <item>Iaundies with obſtruction of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrues. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Windineſſe in the ſtomacke. ibid.</item>
                  <item>Cough of the lungs. 32</item>
                  <item>Another with ſtitch in the ſide. ib.</item>
                  <item>Shortneſſe of breath w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a cough. 32</item>
                  <item>Another. 33</item>
                  <item>To ſtay vomiting. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Vomiting of bloud with a fluxe of the bellie. 34</item>
                  <item>Vomiting with a feuer. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Pluriſie cured. 35</item>
                  <item>Pluriſie with ſpatting of bloud. ibi.</item>
                  <item>Pluriſie with inſlamation of the toung, &amp;c. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Pluriſie in a woman. 36</item>
                  <item>Another for the ſame. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Diaphoretical decoction. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Pluriſie broken with a potion. ibid.</item>
                  <item>Another. 37</item>
                  <item>An inward Apoſteme or baſtard pluriſie. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Payne in the ſide. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Payne and wind in the body. 38</item>
                  <item>Expelling of wind. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Dropſie cured. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Againſt wormes in the ſtomack or elſe where. 39</item>
                  <item>A quartaine of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance. ibi.</item>
                  <item>Againſt the peſtilence, pluriſie &amp; quartaine. 40</item>
                  <item>Swelling of the ſplene. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tick feuers for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſleepe. ib.</item>
                  <item>Peſtilent feuers. 41</item>
                  <item>Againſt poiſon or the peſtilence a Diaphoreticall potion. ibidem</item>
                  <item>The ſignes of death in the plague. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, preſeruatiues, &amp;c. againſt the plague. 42</item>
                  <item>An inueterate Gonorrhea in man or worman. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Another. 43</item>
                  <item>An Electuarie againſt Gonorrhea. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To ſtoppe the immoderate fluxe menſtruall. 44</item>
                  <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To ſtoppe a fluxe. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Bloudy fluxe cured. 45</item>
                  <item>Cures of the Hemorhoides. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ficus in ano.</hi> ibidem</item>
                  <item>To prouoke menſtrues. 46</item>
                  <item>Another of the ſame. ibidem</item>
                  <item>Suffocation of the Matrix. 47</item>
                  <item>Another for the ſame. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To prouoke vrine. ibidem</item>
                  <item>To prouoke vrine and to heale o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſtructions. 48</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>The firſt part of the ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Appendix, &amp;c.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Of paine in the head &amp; the cure. 49</item>
                     <item>Of the catharre and reume in the head. 50</item>
                     <item>The ſecond cauſe to cure the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharre. 51</item>
                     <item>Contuſion in the head. 52</item>
                     <item>The healing of the white ſcall, 53</item>
                     <item>Payne in the eyes. ibidem</item>
                     <item>An vnguent for ſore eyes. ibidem</item>
                     <item>To ſtay ſpatting of bloud. ibidem</item>
                     <item>The deſcription and cure of the Squinancie. ibidem</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18630:7"/>The deſcription and cure, of ſcro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulae. 54</item>
                     <item>Another cure for the ſame. 55</item>
                     <item>Another for the ſame. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Panaricium and the cure. 56</item>
                     <item>Vlcers in womens breaſts. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Aſtma and the cure of it. 57</item>
                     <item>To know a confirmed dropſie. 58</item>
                     <item>Againſt wormes. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Hardnes of the milt &amp; the cure. ibi.</item>
                     <item>Another for the ſame. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of the Gonorrhea &amp; the cure. ibi.</item>
                     <item>Of the Hemorrhoides and their cure. 60</item>
                     <item>Of the diuers ſorts &amp; effects of the Hemorrhoides &amp; their cure. ibi.</item>
                     <item>Suffocation of the matrix and the cure thereof. 61</item>
                     <item>Of the rupture and the cure in the beginning. 62</item>
                     <item>Another. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of rete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of vrine &amp; the cure. 63</item>
                     <item>Of the difficultie of vrine and the cure thereof. 68</item>
                     <item>Another for the ſame often proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of retention of vrine with ſtitch in the ſide. 69</item>
                     <item>Swelling of the legges and feete &amp; their cure. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Chilblaines and their cure. 70</item>
                     <item>Of cornes in the feete and to take them away. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of a greefe vnder the nayles of the fingers and toes and the cure. 71</item>
                     <item>Of Eriſipela &amp; the cure therof. ibi.</item>
                     <item>The cure of wartes. 72</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="appendix">
                  <head>The ſecond part of the Appendix, &amp;c.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Of Danewort and his vertues. 73</item>
                     <item>Of Eleborus niger and his vertues. 73</item>
                     <item>Of Gratia Dei, &amp; the vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 74</item>
                     <item>Of Rubarb and his vſe. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Tithymale and his vertues. 75</item>
                     <item>Of Soldanella and his vertues. 76</item>
                     <item>Of Cyperus and his vertues. ibid.</item>
                     <item>Of Elder and his vertues. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Tabaco and his vſe. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of ſweet Margerom and his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. 77</item>
                     <item>Of Perſicaria and his vſe. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of man and the medecines taken from him. 78</item>
                     <item>Of an henne and the Phiſicall vſe thereof. 79</item>
                     <item>Of Ecles &amp; their medecinal vſe 80</item>
                     <item>Of the Barbill and her vſe in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decine. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Bees &amp; their medecinall vſe. ib.</item>
                     <item>Of Frogs &amp; their Phiſicall vſe. 81</item>
                     <item>Of Centumpedes, Crickets, &amp;c. &amp; their vſe. ibidem</item>
                     <item>Of Tacca mahacca and the vſe thereof. 82</item>
                     <item>Of the gumme Caranna and the vſe thereof. ibidem.</item>
                     <item>Of Liquide amber and the vſe of it in medecine. ibidem.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>In the Epiſtle Dedicatorie, pag 1. lin. 17. for theſe wordes haue euen borne, read theſe haue euer borne. Pag 8 of the booke, lin. 5. for Carton, read Carlton. pag. 40. lin. 11. for Paraceli, read Paracelſi. pag. 54. after the 6. line before the tittle of the Chapter, read CHAP. 111. which is omitted in the number. pag. 3. lin. 6. for you finde, read you ſhall finde. pag. 12 lin. 17. for heate, read heale. pag. 77. laſt line thereof, for our part, read one part. pag. 31, laſt line ſauing one, for vicious cauſe, read, viſcous cauſe. pag. 35. lin. 15. for lb. j read, Pj, page. 48 lin. 3. Adde thid word <hi>Note</hi> in the margent. page. 63. lin. 13. for the vayne, read the vrine.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <div type="proem">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18630:9"/>
               <head>THE PROEME, OR ENTRANCE, INTO THIS COL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LECTION: CONTAINED IN THE firſt foure Chapters.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I</hi> What the dutie of an expert Chirurgian is.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good and true Chirurgian, is no other, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a miniſter and helper of nature: who hath three operations to performe, in curing of woundes. The firſt is, that he ioyne the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated parts cloſe together, the ſecond to preſerue it from paine: the third, that he keepe it from putrifaction: all the reſt he may leaue vnto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which will worke with good expedition. And this is a ſure intention: concerning the cure of woundes. Neuer keepe the fleſh open, with tents or pledgets, neither weaken nature, by letting of bloud, or by purging, nor yet by ſtrait diet, to cauſe the paine to increaſe, but keepe the wound al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes cleane, waſhing it with <hi>Aqua balſami;</hi> and lay vpon the wound, clothes wette in <hi>Magno licore.</hi> This is a good, and an approued order: whereof whoſoeuer wil know more, let him looke in <hi>Leonardo Fiorauante</hi> his booke, of <hi>Rational ſecrets,</hi> where he ſhall be ſatisfied more at large.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II</hi> The cure of all manner of vvoundes in generall.</head>
                  <p>ALl kinde of woundes, may be healed, with theſe mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines following (according to the method before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18630:10"/>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> with our <hi>balſamo,</hi> with <hi>Aqua balſami, balſamum artificiale, quintaeſſentia vini, oleum reſinae pini, oleum cerae &amp; terebinthinae, magno licore, cerotum magistrale, elixir vitae, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum hypericonis compoſitum,</hi> our ſecret powder, all which are ſet downe, in the forenamed booke, and for the moſt part, are to be had, for a reaſonable conſideration, at the houſe of <hi>M. Iames Foureſtier,</hi> ſtudent in Phiſicke dwelling in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, in the <hi>Black Friers,</hi> betweene the two tenneſe courts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The cauſe vvhy vvounds cannot heale quicklie.</head>
                  <p>THough there be many more, yet chieflie they may be reduced vnto two cauſes. The one is an immoderate &amp; extreme diet, which weakneth the ſtomack and body ſo much, that nature cannot preuaile, to conglutinate or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fleſh together. And thus thorough want of naturall heate, the wound falleth to impoſtemation, <hi>Gangrena, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulaes. &amp;c.</hi> and can hardly be cured. The ſecond cauſe is, the keeping of them to much open, by reaſon of their tents or pledgets, ſo that they cannot ioyne together agayne, but grow to Cancers, and Fiſtulaes, whereupon many times, the patient remaineth lame euer after, or elſe ſpeedie death is the end thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of vvoundes in the head, how they must be dealt vvithall.</head>
                  <p>ALl wounds in the head, muſt be cloſe ioyed and kept together, the bloud muſt be cruſhed out, then waſh it well, with ſome-thing that hath vertue to liquifie the bloud, as the <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> of wine, or ſuch like. Then lay thereon lint, wet in <hi>oleum benedictum:</hi> this medecine you ſhall change in foure dayes, but euery day once waſh the wound round about, with that <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> and annoint with the ſaid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18630:10"/>
oyle, and at the fourth dayes end, dreſſe it agayne, and let it remaine two dayes more, &amp; after that for a day more, &amp; the wound (by the helpe of God) ſhalbe cured in xij. or xiiij. dayes. Thus may you deale, with all wounds, ſaue thoſe, that are made in the bellie. As for all other, either ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound wounds: you finde their cure, methodically ſhewed, in the <hi>Rationall ſecrets,</hi> of <hi>Leonardo Fiorauante</hi> publiſhed in Engliſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V</hi> The healing of a greeuous vvound on the ſide of the head.</head>
                  <p>THe wound was made, on the ſide of the head, almoſt to <hi>dura mater:</hi> and it was healed in this manner. Firſt there was put into the ſame, the <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> aforſaid, then a litle <hi>balſamo,</hi> then there was applied a cloth which was wet in <hi>magno licore,</hi> made very hote, vpon which cloth, was layd our ſecret powder, couered with lint, and thus he was dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, once euery day, till he was whole. You muſt note, that whenſoeuer the ſcull is hurt, vnto <hi>dura mater,</hi> there muſt be caſt vp at the noſethrilles, our <hi>balſamo:</hi> that the ſmell may pierce vpward, and reſolue the offence. Sometime alſo, in ſtead of a defenſatiue, you may annoint round about the wound, with the foreſaid <hi>balme;</hi> which preſerueth from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction, and alteration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A daungerous vvound in the head, cured in fiue dayes.</head>
                  <p>IT was healed very quicklie, by putting therein our <hi>Aqua caeleſtis,</hi> and <hi>balſamo,</hi> and by applying vnto the ſame, very hote clothes, wet in <hi>magno licore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The cure of a vvound, on the eare to the ſcull.</head>
                  <p>A Sore wound was made on the care, which was cut vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſcull of the head, and was healed in this manner:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18630:11"/>
firſt by annointing it with our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> which cauſed it to waxe very hote, the ſpace of two houres. After that, there was put in, our <hi>oleum philoſophorum, de terebinthina &amp; cera,</hi> and ſo he dreſſed it euery day once.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> How three vvounds in the head, vvith fracture of the bone or ſcull vvere healed by <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine miller in Buckinghamſhire, called <hi>Peter Bull,</hi> being ſore wounded in the head, whereof one wound was in the midſt of the head, with fracture of the ſcull, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within an inch of that, ſix inches long, he had an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wound, ouer his eyebrow two inches long. Beſides the woundes in his head, he had alſo a great wound, in the bowt of his arme, beſide the elbow, ſo that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might haue layd: his three ſingers in it, diuers of his fingers were alſo cut, and he loſt two ioynts. This man bled by the ſpace of ſeuen or eight houres, before it was ſtinted: neither was he dreſſed, vntill the next day, but yet he was cured in this manner. Firſt the haire was ſhauen away, round about the woundes on his head, and the wounds were made cleane, then was there dropped into the wound, <hi>balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warme: and a ſine cloth wet therein was applied to the wounds, and round about the wounds there was a defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue applied: thus he was dreſſed once in 24. houres, and within the ſpace of three weekes, he was perfectly holpen, that he ware no plaſter at all. Alſo you ſhall note that vpon the wound, next the cloth, there was layd <hi>cerotum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrale,</hi> of <hi>Leonardo Fiorauante:</hi> Forget not that this bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame muſt alwayes be vſed warme, with a fine linnen cloth, or a peece of Cambrick, and not with any lint. This bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame did cauſe the haire to grow ſo faſt about the wounds: that it was fayne to be ſhauen away verie often.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18630:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of contuſed vvounds on the head or other parts of the bodie.</head>
                  <p>THe auncient practitioners, haue eſteemed contuſed wounds to be verie dangerous. For they ſay contuſions muſt firſt be brought to putrifactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; turned into matter: which opinion is not to be allowed, for the bruſes are to be diſſolued without maturatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hath bene a thouſand times proued in the warres, after this manner to haue bene performed. <hi>Recipe, magno licore, oleum benedictum, ana,</hi> mixe them, &amp; being verie hote, wet clothes therein, &amp; lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on twiſe a day, and in three or foure dayes they wilbe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Alſo the oyle of Franckinſence, or <hi>oleu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> philoſophorum de tereb. &amp; cera,</hi> will reſolue any ſimple bruiſe in three or foure houres, only by continual annointing the place therewith, ſo faſt as it drinketh in any. Prouided, that the bruiſe be not aboue ſix or eight houres old, for if it be, then will your worke be ſomwhat the longer, before it be finiſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> A contuſed vvound in the head, healed by <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Young man of 28. yeares of age, that had a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſion on the head with a ſtaffe, was helped thereof in nine dayes; by applying thereunto <hi>balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> A vvound in the head, vvith fracture of the ſcull, cured by <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Litle boy, with a fall from an horſe, had a fracture in the ſcull, which was healed with <hi>balſamum ſulſuris, &amp; cerotum magiſtrale Leonardo.</hi> The child, did at his dreſſing, vomite verie often: which argued the breaking of his ſcull, yet was he healed in ſeuen dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18630:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> To heale vvoundes ſpeedily.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt waſh them verie well with our <hi>aqua balſami,</hi> then ioyne them verie cloſe together, and lay thereon a cloth wet in <hi>olco reſinae pini:</hi> and (through Gods helpe) they ſhall quickly be healed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> To heale vvounds, by ſhot, or launce.</head>
                  <p>HE that will cure woundes, that are made with ſhot, launce, arrowes, &amp;c. muſt firſt waſh the wound well with vrine, &amp; dry the wound well, then let him put therein the <hi>Quintaeſſ.</hi> of wine and forthwith ioyne the wound cloſe &amp; hard together. Then let him put immediatly therein, fiue or ſix drops of our <hi>balſamo artific.</hi> and lay a cloth vpon the wound, wet in <hi>magno licore,</hi> which muſt be applied ſo hote, as he may ſuffer it: thus muſt he do the firſt day. That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, he muſt put thereon our <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> of wine, &amp; then a litle <hi>balſamo,</hi> after that, ſome <hi>magno licore</hi> (as before was ſaid) and ſo let him hold on, vnto the end of his cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> A moſt ſingular and vvonderfull remedie, to heale vvoundes quicklie.</head>
                  <p>VVOunds muſt be holpen, with drying medecines, (as was noted in the third Chapter) ſuch mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines I ſay, as haue vertue, to preſerue the part offended, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putrifaction. This will be performed with our <hi>aqua balſami,</hi> and the oyle diſtilled from vernice liquide: for theſe two, are apt to heale all ſortes of wounds: if ye waſh them with the water and annoint them round about with the oyle, for they do not onely keepe the wounds from putrifying, but they helpe to cicatriſe quicklie, and in ſuch manner, as it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18630:12"/>
ſeemeth maruailous, moſt profitable for the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but beſt for the good and honeſt Surgeon, which abhorreth in his worke, to play the tinker, which in ſtopping of one hole, is wont to make three, but with as much ſafetie and ſpeed, as nature and art will yeld, to bring to paſſe all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intentions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> A vvound in the eye, vvith a ſplinter, healed by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Splinter of wood, leapt into the eye of a certaine mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as ſhe was chopping of ſtickes. The wound was ſo grieuous, that the gellie of her eye came forth, by the ſpace of a moneth: all this while, ſhe could neither ſee, nor take any reſt. By the bleſſing of God within foure dayes after, ſhe could thred a needle, and was recouered in this manner. Firſt there was dropped into her eye, <hi>balſamum ſulfuris</hi> warme, and then a cloth wet therein, was applied thereunto by which onely ſhe was cured: the maid dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in Nottinghamſhire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> A pricke in the eye, vvith a knife, healed by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Child of ſeuen yeares of age, had a puncture in the eye, with a knife, which was cured, by dropping therein, <hi>balſamum ſulfuris</hi> warme, and laying a defenſatiue round about it.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another cure performed in like manner by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe <hi>George Clarke,</hi> ſeruant to the right worſhipfull, <hi>M. Butler</hi> of Denham (then high Sheriffe of Bedford) was healed, of a punct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> in his eye, with the foreſaid medecine.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18630:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> An hand flat ſquatted, and contuſed, healed by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN old man, called <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> of Carton in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amptonſhire, husbandman, in lopping of a tree, had his hand caught betweene two boughes, and was ſquatted in peeces; this contuſed hand, was preſently put cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and annointed which <hi>oleum philoſophorum de Tereb, &amp; cera,</hi> and through Gods goodneſſe, was perfectly cured in eight dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> A vvou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or puncture thorough the arme. <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Young man called <hi>Hudſon,</hi> a Carpenter of Carlton in Northamptonſhire, being thruſt thorough the arme, with a pitchforke, was thus cured. Firſt there was iniected <hi>Magno licore</hi> (as hote as he could abide it) into the wound. Then was there a linnen cloth, wett in the ſame oyle, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto the wound, vpon the which cloth, was alſo layd, a pledget, of <hi>cerotum magiſtrale:</hi> this wounded man was healed in fiue or ſixe dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Fiue vvoundes in the breſt.</head>
                  <p>A Certaine man, that had fiue ſtocadoes into the body, was thus cured. Firſt there was put into the woundes, the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of wine. Then were the woundes dreſſed, with <hi>balſamo artific.</hi> which cauſed him to vomite, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid much bruiſed bloud. After that he dranke, euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a litle <hi>aqua balſami,</hi> and in ſhort time by Gods helpe was perfectly cured.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The manner to ſtay anie fluxe of bloud, or vayne: you ſhall finde in the</hi> 17. <hi>Chapter of the ſecond part of this collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in the ſecrets of Leonardo Fiorauante, vvhere he intreateth of vvoundes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18630:13"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE FIRST DIVISION.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Erbum ſapienti ſat est,</hi> and a man may know by the halfe, what the whole meanes. By theſe few experimented ſecretes, you may proceede, vnto the cure of any wound, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſion, or puncture: in what part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſoeuer they ſhalbe. The things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are to worke, as <hi>balſamum ſulfuris, oleum philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum de Terebinth. &amp; cera, cerotum magiſtrale, &amp;c.</hi> you may haue of <hi>M. Iames Foreſtier;</hi> dwelling in the Blacke fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Now let vs proceede vnto the experimented ſecretes, concerning Vlcers, and Sores, either ſimple, or compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with diſeaſes, as they haue bene obſerued, by thoſe which haue proued them.</p>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> The healing of ſore mouthes.</head>
                  <p>THe Vlcers and Sores, that haue bene, in the mouthes of young and old, haue bene healed, by the lotion or gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſme, made with plantaine water, honie ſuckle water, and barlie water, mixed with <hi>ſaccarum Saturni.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> An Vlcer in the vpper lippe.</head>
                  <p>A Certaine porter of London, hauing an Vlcer on his vpper lippe, which was like a cancer (ſome called it <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li me tangere</hi>) continuallie running, with filthie ſtinking <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> was thus cured. Firſt he was purged, with <hi>Turpetum
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18630:14"/>
minerale:</hi> then was the ſore dreſſed with this medecine.</p>
                  <p>℞. <hi>aloes lotae,</hi> ℥ ſs, <hi>ſalis preparati, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij, Mellis ℥ iiij, miſce, &amp; vtere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> An Vlcer in the throte, ex morbo Gallico.</head>
                  <p>A Young woman, that was much troubled in the throte, with a greeuous Vlcer, was thus cured. Firſt ſhe was purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> &amp; twiſe or thriſe with our <hi>Quinta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence ſolutiue,</hi> mixed with <hi>ſyrupe</hi> of roſes, then was the ſore touched, with <hi>Aquarealis,</hi> two or three times, with a litle lint, and laſtly ſhe vſed this gargariſme.</p>
                  <p>℞. <hi>mellis roſarum, ℥ ij, Diamorum, ℥ ij</hi> ſs, honie ſuckle wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>ana ℥ vi. oleum vitrioli,</hi> as much as will ſuffice, to make it tart: this hath bene often proued in daungerous caſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> The healing of a ſcald head.</head>
                  <p>A Woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had all her head couered, with a moſt filthy ſcab, which was dry aboue, and moiſt vnderneath, very noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to behold, who could neither be healed, by purging, or locall medecines, that were vſed, till this medecine was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto her. Once in a day, <hi>oleu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ligni guaiaci,</hi> was applied, and in ſhort time, the ſcall fell away, like a ſcull of an head, and there began haire to grow vnderneath it: this cure was performed in twelue dayes.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another cure performed vpon a ſcald head.</head>
                     <p>A Maiden of eighteen yeares of age, hauing an huge great ſcall vpon her head, was cured (after ſhe had taken one doſe of <hi>Aromatico</hi>) by often waſhing the part affected, with <hi>Mater balſami Fiorauante.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> An Vlcer on the thombe.</head>
                  <p>ONe had ſuch a filthie, &amp; ſtinking Vlcer on the thumbe, that the Chirurgians, would haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the whole
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18630:14"/>
thumbe. This partie was afterward cured, by the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Fodicationum emplaſtri.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> An Vlcerated legge ſwolne.</head>
                  <p>A Young boy, that had an vlcerated legge wonderfully ſwolne, was thus cured. He receaued at two ſeuerall times, <hi>Quintaeſſ. ſolutiue,</hi> with ſyrupe of roſes. Then were the ſores waſhed, with ſalt of vitrioll, diſſolued in plantaine water: a cloth being wet therein, and applied thereto mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Two putrified <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers on the legge healed by <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt this patient was purged, with <hi>Aromatico Leon,</hi> once or twiſe: then his Vlcers were dreſſed, with this vngue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, made of rubified vitrioll: and a cerote, called the great Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rote. This was applied vnto the Vlcers, with a pledget of lint, and was ſuffred to lye 24. houres, which mortified the ſores. Then was more of the ſame vnguent applied, and with an inſtrument the eſcare was looſed round about, and in three or foure dayes, the eſcare came away eaſily, with a paire of Mullets: then he healed it vp, with <hi>Magno licore,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſaccarum plumbi,</hi> within a litle while after.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> Three Vlcers in the legge, healed by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine woman of Bedford, had three Vlcers in her legge, who had ſought her cure, at the hands of diuers, the ſpace of foure yeares, but could finde no helpe, yet ſhe was afterward cured in this manner. Firſt ſhe tooke in the morning faſting <hi>Aromatico Leonardo,</hi> which euacuated her ſtomack and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ie. Then was there applied vnto the ſores,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18630:15"/>
                     <hi>ſaccarum plumbi,</hi> three or foure dayes togither, which cauſed euerie day, a certaine thinne skin to come vpon the Vlcers, much like the filme of an egge, the ſame skin was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away euery day. With this medecine following, it was dreſſed the fourth day: which cauſed it, to looke faire, and red, the next dreſſing: and ſo in ſhort time it was perfectly cured. To one ſpoonfull of <hi>magno licore</hi> was put as much <hi>ſaccaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Saturni,</hi> as would lye vpon a three pence;: and ſo it was incorporated warme: the ſores were dreſſed therewith euerie day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> The cure of old rotten ſores by <hi>W. R.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine old woman, did in this manner, helpe diuers old ſores in the body. Firſt ſhe purged the patients, and then ſhe applied this vnguent to the ſores. Take a pot of ſtrong ale, and ſet it to boile ouer a gentle fire, till it wax thicke, like a ſalue, and then vſe it. At the firſt this medecine will ſmart, and be ſomewhat painfull to beare, neuertheleſſe it will clenſe and heate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note>Alſo a freind of mine told me, that the iuice of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold leaues, or the leaues, boiled with milke to an vnguent, will heale all vlcers and woundes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> The healing of vlcers, in moſt parts of the bodie: but chieflie in the head by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine man being full of vlcers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the pocks, in moſt parts of his bodie ſhewing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the head, was cured in this manner. Firſt he was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, twiſe or thriſe, with <hi>Panchimagogon,</hi> after that, he kept his chamber, (that had a good ſire in it) and tooke ſix graines of <hi>Turpetum diaphoreticum,</hi> mixed with <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j of <hi>Amuletu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marij.</hi> Halfe an houre before, he tooke a draught of fat broth, and kept his bed: and alwayes as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ited, he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18630:15"/>
his mouth, with a conuenient gargariſme, and ſweat thereon, one houre or two, and then was dried with warme clothes: That done, he repoſed a day or two, and tooke the foreſaid <hi>Turpetum</hi> agayne, in manner aforeſaid: this he did three or foure times. In the meane while, he annointed his vlcers with <hi>oleum guaiaci,</hi> which did both clenſe, and heale. Alſo diuers times, he vſed this potio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the morning, which cauſed him to ſweat. ℞. ℥ ij of the water of <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> made by diſtillation, and as much of the ſirrupe of fumitorie, and ℈ j of the ſalt of <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> mixe them warme, and drinke it faſting. Thus in verie ſhort time he was cured. This one thing muſt not be forgotten, that when there ſhall come, any inflammation or ſoreneſſe in the mouth, you do vſe this gargariſme following. Take plantaine water, honie ſuckle water, <hi>ana</hi> ℥ iiij, barlie water, ℥ vi. <hi>mel roſarum</hi> ℥ ij ſs, <hi>Diamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> ℥ ij, <hi>oleu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitrioli,</hi> as much as will make it tart: this will heale any ſore in the mouth. Remember alſo, that if the vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers be very corroſiue, and foule, you ſhall touch them, once or twiſe, with <hi>oleum vitrioli</hi> or <hi>oleum tartari faetens,</hi> whereby they will heale the ſooner, this hath bene often proued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> The healing of ſcabs, like the leproſie, by <hi>G. M.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Young man (which was thought to be infected with a leproſie) had on his head, and moſt partes of his bodie, hard and drie ſcabs, but he was cured in this manner. Firſt he was purged with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo</hi> once or twiſe. Then euerie morning till he was cured, he tooke ℈ j of the extract of <hi>Camepiteos,</hi> either in a pill, or in drinke as he thought good. After that, his ſores were dreſſed, with this vnguent. ℞. <hi>ſucci ſemperumi</hi> ℥ ij, <hi>ſucei plantaginis</hi> ℥ iiij ſs, <hi>ſucci ſolani</hi> ℥ iij, <hi>ſacchari Saturni</hi> ℥ ij, ſs, mixe them, and ſtirre them well together ouer a gentle fire, till all the <hi>ſaccharum</hi> be diſſolued, and therewith dreſſe the ſores twiſe a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18630:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> The healing of a child, that vvas full of vlcers, comming of the pockes.</head>
                  <p>A Young child foure yeares old, that was grieuouſlie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the French diſeaſe, hauing extreme payne in his bodie, and being full of ſores, was thus cured. ℞ the diſtilled water of <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> ℥ j, <hi>ſalis eiuſdem</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, mixe them, and thereof the child dranke, with ſirupe of furnitorie or hops, morning and euening, and ſometime the child ſweat thereon. Alſo the ſores were annointed, with this vnguent, ℞. <hi>oleum guaiaci,</hi> ℥ ſs, <hi>balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, <hi>ſaccarum plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi,</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, <hi>oleum camphorae,</hi> fiue or ſix drops, the <hi>caput mortuum</hi> of <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> ℈ j. Mixe them well, and grind them on a ſtone, with May butter, &amp; therewith the ſores were annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted morning and euening.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> A cancer cured by an old Empericke.</head>
                  <p>A Certaine Empericke, did helpe many cancers, in diuers people (that were troubled with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. He tooke certaine wormes, called in Latine <hi>Centumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> in Engliſh ſowes: they are ſuch as lye vnder old timber, or betweene the barke and the tree. Theſe he ſtamped, and ſtrained with ale, &amp; gaue the patient to drinke thereof mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening. This medecine cauſed many times, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine blacke bugge, or worme to come forth which had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny legs, &amp; was quicke: &amp; after that the cancker would heale quicklie, with any conuenient medecine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> The healing of pockie puſtules, vvith Serpigo by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine man, hauing a number of ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, all ouer his bodie, &amp; a <hi>ſerpigo</hi> in the palme of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd, ſo grieuous,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18630:16"/>
that a man might haue layd great ſtrawes therein, was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this manner. Firſt he was purged three times, with ſix graines of <hi>Turpetum minerale Phaedronis,</hi> mixed with halfe a dramme of <hi>Amuletum Palmarij.</hi> That done, he annointed all his ſores twiſe or thrife, with <hi>oleum Tartari foetens:</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with <hi>vnguentum ex Lithargirio Fiorauante.</hi> Now tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his handes, which had the <hi>ſerpigo,</hi> he held them mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; euening, ouer a bath of otes, or other warme herbes, that they might ſweat: and then annointed them, with <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamum ſulfuris,</hi> and in ſhort time they were holpen. An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent made with <hi>ſaccarum Saturni</hi> and oyle of roſes, will do the like effect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXIIII.</hi> A tetter or ringworme, cured by <hi>W. K.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is a certaine worme or tetter, which manie times co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth on the backe of the hand or arme, &amp; doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode, like a <hi>ſerpigo,</hi> but it is none, which (after the vſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other medecines) hath bene cured in this manner. The place was annointed 5. or ſix times a day, with the ſirupe of ſugar, that the worme might come to the vpper place or skin. Then within three or foure dayes after, he annointed the place with <hi>oleum Tartari foetens:</hi> &amp; in ſhort time he was cured, though his diſeaſe, had continued three yeares, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and going. Some haue killed the worme, with <hi>oleum vitrioli.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> A man cured, that vvas full of tetters.</head>
                  <p>THis was the manner of his cure. He tooke the rennet of a calfe, and dronke it in milke three or foure times, and ſweat thereupon: then he annointed the partes affected, with <hi>ſaccarum Saturni,</hi> mixed with byle of roſes warme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18630:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> Tetters in vvomens breaſtes, oftentimes cured as followeth,</head>
                  <p>THey tooke fiue ſponfulls of Madder, and boiled it in ale, and then ſtrained it cleare, without preſſing it at all, and dronke thereof, three or foure mornings. Then with the foreſaid ointment, they vſed to annoint the partes grieued, and thereupon (with Gods helpe) were quicklie healed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> The healing of Shingles.</head>
                  <p>THey tooke for them, doues dong newly made; and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meale; ſtamped them well, and mixed them with halfe a pint of vineger: they vſed it cold, to the place grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and applied vine leaues (to keepe in the liquor) round about it. Then they bound it vp with clothes, and ſuffered it to lye three dayes, and then (if neede were) refreſhed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne with a new plaiſter, and at the moſt, with the vſe of three applications, it was perfectlie holpen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> The breaking of a plague ſore, by <hi>W. K.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HE tooke of elder leaues, as much as was ſufficient, he ſtamped them verie well with drie figs, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>auxungiae porcinae,</hi> and applied it warme to the ſore, three or foure times a day, and it quicklie brake it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> Scabs and itch, vvith ſmall puſtules, taken quite away by <hi>I. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine man greatly troubled, with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hand puſtules, in his hands, proceeding of a diſſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in his body,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18630:17"/>
could finde no helpe, till he vſed this courſe. He tooke <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimagogon,</hi> twiſe in three dayes: that done, he waſhed his handes, with the ſalt of vitrioll diſſolued in plantaine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſhortlie after they went quite away.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Three deepe fiſtulaes in the breaſt, cured by <hi>W. T.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere was a certaine man, called <hi>R. B.</hi> dwelling in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which hauing three deepe fiſtulaes in his breaſt, had bene long vnder the hands of vnskilfull Chirurgians, conſuming both himſelfe and his ſubſtance: but afterward by Gods helpe, he vſing the courſe, that <hi>W. T.</hi> preſcribed, was cured verie ſpeedilie. Firſt he was purged euery ſecond or third day for fiue or ſixe times together, with <hi>Turpetum minerale Phaedronis,</hi> receauing thereof fiue or ſix graines in <hi>Amul: Palmarij.</hi> Afterward, he was cauſed to ſweat fiue or ſix times, with this potion following.</p>
                  <p>℞. the diſtilled water of <hi>lignum vitae ℥ ij, ſalis eiuſdem</hi> ℈ j, water of <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> ℥ ij, which being mixed, he dronke it warme in the morning, and ſweat thereon two houres. After he was purged, he dreſſed the fiſtulaes two houres, with this vnguent (vntill they were mundified) vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tents of ſhoe leather. When the fiſtulaes were clenſed, he dreſſed them only with <hi>Emplaſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fodicationis</hi> (being made liquide, to wrap vp the tent with) till they where whole.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The mundificatiue ointment vvas this.</head>
                     <p>℞. oyle of waxe, of <hi>ſuccinum,</hi> of <hi>guaiacum, oleum hyperic. compoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij,</hi> mixe them without ſire &amp; vſe it with the aforeſaid tents. Alſo you ſhall note, that he dronke no other drinke then this, all the while. ℞. <hi>lignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitae,</hi> the barke, <hi>ſarſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parilla, ana ℥ iiij,</hi> the rootes of Torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>till, <hi>Biſtorta, virga pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoris,</hi> liquorice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ℥ <hi>ij,</hi> Iuniper berries, ℥ j, Mallow leaues, Sanicle, Alchim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mugwort, Hypericon, Brunella, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18630:18"/>
                        <hi>ana M ij.</hi> Bring theſe into powder and for euery gallon of new tunned drinke, adde thereto, two or three ounces of this powder, in a linnen cloth: let it ſtand till it be ſtale, and let him drinke thereof.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> The cure of Lichen, or Impetigo, by <hi>M. K.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Certaine maiden 17. yeares old, had all the fleſh on her thombe, and forefinger eaten away, with the foreſayd diſeaſe: which was cured by ſtrawing thereon <hi>ſaccaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> and applying thereto <hi>Cerotum magiſtrale Fiorauante.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> A great vvenne taken away by, <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>ONe that was troubled, with a great wenne, had it taken away, by waſhing it with ſtrong lye made of oken aſhes. I haue bene ſince told, of a certaintie, that if ye rubbe the wenne often, with the hand of a dead man, vntill the wenne waxe hote, it will conſume away in ſhort time after. Some roſt an egge hard, and cut it in the midſt, and lay it thereon and vſing this often the wenne will weare away.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18630:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND PART CONCERNING THE CVRES OF INTERNALL DISEASES.</hi> Thus much brieflie, in theſe ſhort Chapters, is expreſſed and declared, concerning vvoundes and vlcers: vvhereſoeuer they be, or howſoeuer they ariſe. By vvhich examples, the learned artiſt, may vndertake other things, vvhich are not here mentioned. But in any caſe, let him be aduiſed by the vviſe Phiſitian, in his buſineſſe, vvhen there is any difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and not runne by and by to his receit or experiment. It followeth now (in manner aforeſaid) to ſet down the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued practiſes of thoſe that haue cured internall diſeaſes, vvhich haue taken effect, and brought forth ſyntomes, outwardlie or inwardlie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the cure of grieuous aches, and payne, performed, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Certaine man was greatly afflicted, with diuers wofull aches, and paines in his knees and ſhoulders, who was cured, by receauing a doſe of <hi>Aromatico,</hi> and by application of <hi>emplaſtrum faetidum,</hi> vnto the grieued parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The healing of aches, comming of the pockes, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe of a ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> darke and melancholike complexion, to whom ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in London, had giuen the fume, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18630:19"/>
the vnction, three or foure times: and yet left him poſſeſſed with moſt pitifull aches and paine in his ioynts; who for want of maintenance, was inforced to go into the countrie, where he was borne, and was there pittied of an honeſt Gentleman, which cured him in this ſort. Firſt he purged him twiſe or thriſe with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo:</hi> which done, he tooke for foure or fiue dayes together, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, of the extract of <hi>Hermodactiles,</hi> with white wine. Then vnto the articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar parts that were g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieued, he applied <hi>emplastrum faetidum, W. H.</hi> and thus in ſhort time he was healed throughlie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A notable experience, of a medecine that hath brought great eaſe, to any great ache or paine, as of the gout or otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>TAke one or two, of the formoſt ſucking whelpes, of a maſtif or bearebitch, kill them, and take ſorth the guts, fill them with blacke ſnailes, roſt them, and baſt them with ℥ xij, of oyle of ſpike, coloured with ſaffron. Reſerue that, which droppeth from them, and mixe it with as much oyle of waxe, and therewith annoint any ache or grief.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> A particular vvay vvhereby the paine of the gout is ſoone eaſed or preuented, <hi>S. N.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>minium,</hi> the yolke of an egge, oyle of tartar, oyle of roſes, as much of ech as you thinke ſufficient, and with a litle ſaffran make it in forme of a plaiſter, and lay it on cold. I knew an other Gentleman, grieuouſlie vexed with the goute, who was in this ſort ſoone eaſed. Firſt when he ſuppoſed that the payne would come, he tooke a doſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romatico Leonardo:</hi> then the next day, vnto thoſe grieued parts, he applied this plaiſter. Take a pickle herring, and cut forth the bone, ſtampe it verie ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a litle <hi>bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18630:19"/>
and roſe water, and apply it cold to the grief, from place to place, as it goeth. Many men, after they haue bene well purged, haue had great eaſe by annointing the place, three or foure nights together, with <hi>aqua balſami Fioraua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</hi> Alſo <hi>oleum cerae,</hi> is verie profitable in that caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The cure of goutes, and all aches, comming of heate, by <hi>L. F.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt the patients were purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then was this plaiſter applied, which is attractiue, reſiccatiue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutiue, as being intentions farre better fitting that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, then any other. Take the marrow, of the bones of a calfe new killed, <abbr>lb</abbr> j vitrioll in manner rubified, <abbr>lb</abbr> j ſs, <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarides</hi> in ſine powder, ℥ j, the aſhes of the vine, ℥ vi, mixe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all on a ſmall fire, vntill they be incorporated, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with oile of waxe, make it in a liquide ointment, and ſpread it on a cloth, and lay it on cold. And when it waxeth drie, chafe it till the paine be ceaſed: this hath eaſed many in a ſhort time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The remedie againſt the Scorbute or Scuruie, and the goute, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Young man of 26. yeares of age, mightilie troubled with the goute, and ſcuruie was after this ſorr cured. Firſt he was purged with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo.</hi> Then he vſed the purging drinke following euerie morning, that he might haue ech day 3. or foure ſtooles. At night, he tooke two ounces, of the diſtilled water of <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> with ℥ j of the ſirupe of Couſlips. Alſo he vſed to eate, theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues following mixed together. ℞. conſerue of Couſlips ℥ iiij. of ſage, of roſemarie flowres, <hi>ana,</hi> ℥ ij. of red roſes ℥ j. The quantitie which he tooke at once, was as much as a walnut. Alſo he annointed the grieued partes with this vnguent. ℞. <hi>auxungiae humanae</hi> diſtilled ℥ ij, oyle of Turpentine, ℥ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of waxe ℥ ſs, mixe them together. Alſo in his vſuall dru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, which he dronke with his meate, was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18630:20"/>
mixed <hi>Chamepiteos,</hi> ſage, roſemarie, and betonie, this was the purging drinke. ℞ the ſtrong decoction of <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> put therein of the leaues of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ℥ iiij. <hi>Epithimum</hi> ℥ ij, <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dactiles</hi> ℥ iiij, <hi>Turbith</hi> ℥ j, <hi>Coloquintid.</hi> ℥ ſs. let them ſtand in warme ſand 24. houres and ſtrayne it, this he dronke in the morning faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Tumors in all partes of the bodie, taken away, by <hi>R. A.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis was ſent me by a freind of mine, who had ſeene the experience thereof diuers times. Firſt he purged the patients twiſe, with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo:</hi> then he gaue vnto them ℥ ij of <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> with ℥ j of ſirupe of roſes, foure or fiue mornings together: and after it, they dranke a litle good broth made ſweet with ſugar: that done, they dronke this water following. ℞. herbegrace, ſothernwood, mugwort, wormwood, <hi>ana M</hi> j. Iuniper berries, three or foure handfull, cut the herbes and bruiſe the berries, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them in a gallon of white wine vineger .24. houres in a warme place. Then diſtill it with a gentle fire. This done, take that diſtilled vineger, and infuſe therein freſh herbes &amp; berries, and diſtill it agayne as afore. Do ſo the third time, and diſtill it as afore. At the laſt infuſion, you ſhall put therein ℥ iiij of good Mitridate, or Triacle, and diſtill them together, and keepe them cloſe to your vſe. Thereof the patients tooke, at foure a clocke in the morning, ℥ iiij, verie warme, whereupon they layd them downe and ſweat, two or three houres, alway wiping it away with warme clothes. Euery ſweating tyme, they changed their ſhirtes. When this medecine was miniſtred to a woman, ſhe tooke but ℥ ij thereof. To a child he gaue ℥ ij. In this ſort, he cured not onelie Tumors, but ſores, puſtules, feuers, laundies, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18630:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Swelling of the coddes mitigated and reſolued, by <hi>R. A.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine man, riding on a trotting horſe, had his ſtones ſwolne, as big as ones fiſt, who was thus holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Firſt he was purged once or twiſe, with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chimagogon,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taplaſme was applied warme, vnto the part twiſe or thriſe a day. ℞. the crums of browne bread, beane flowre, <hi>ana</hi> as much as is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, boile them with new wort; when it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt boiled, put thereto a litle Comminſced, and a diſh of freſh butter, and ſo applie it warme. I haue ſeene the fat of an horſe, to haue cured the foreſaid griefe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take a pint of pure honie, as much beane ſlower, and two ſpoonfuls of vineger, of Comminſeed ℥ ij, mixe them well together, and ſpread it on a cloth, and warme it a litle againſt the fire, and applie it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The cure of a painfull Iſchiatica, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine man, that was grieuouſly troubled with the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiatica,</hi> was healed in this manner. Firſt he was purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then he tooke for fiue or ſix mornings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, two drammes of <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> with ſirupe of roſes, and after the taking therof he dronke a litle ſweet broth. That done, he drew a bliſter with <hi>Cantarides,</hi> and when it had runne inough, he annointed the place, with <hi>oleum de terebinth. &amp; cera;</hi> and in ſhort time he was holpen. Since which time, I haue knowen three or foure perſons holpen in the ſame manner, by annointing the grieued parts with <hi>Aqua balſami Fiorauante.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> An excellent remedie, againſt the crampe, proued often, by <hi>R. G.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey that were affected therewith, did vpon their bare skin &amp; places grieued, weare the roote of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Flagge.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18630:21"/>
Alſo the skins of twentie ſiluer eeles, new fleane, and chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſmall, boiled in two pound of May butter, and foure handful of Rue, ſcumme it well, and annoint the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with worke the ſame effect. A worſhipfull Gentleman, that had diuers times proued the ſame, ſent theſe notes vnto me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Contraction or ſhrinking of ſinewes, vvith conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the partie, holpen, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man 26. yeares old, hauing a ſore and grieuous vlcerated legge, fell into the handes of inexpert Surgeons, who with their corroſiues ſhrunke vp his ſinewes, that he could neither go nor ſtand, but in ſhort time after, he was cured in this manner. He was once purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then he tooke <hi>Quintaeſſe: ſolutiue</hi> two or 3. dayes together, in ſirupe of roſes, and dronke thereupon a litle broth. Then did he vſe the bath following diuers times, &amp; annointed him with the ointment, againſt contraction of ſinewes, deſcribed by <hi>Leonardo Fioraua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</hi> Another man hauing his hand ſhrunke together, vpon the like occaſion, was healed in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This is the deſcription of the bath. Take two or three young whelpes, that cannot ſee, boile them in water with mallowes, Hollihock, mellilot, walwort, Camomill, <hi>ana</hi> one handfull: boile the whelpes, till the fleſh fall from the bones, this done ſtrayne it, and vſe to bath therewith very warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> The cure of one, vvhoſe necke vvas drawen awrie, performed, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Child had her necke drawen awrie, with a kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulſion, or crampe called <hi>Tetanus,</hi> and was thus cured. Firſt ſhe dronke, euerie morning and euening, a litle <hi>Aqua balſami Fiorauante,</hi> then was her necke annointed, with ſome of the ſayd water mixed with <hi>Magno licore Fiorauante,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18630:21"/>
in ten dayes ſhe was cured.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Oleum de lateribus.</hi> ℥ i, <hi>Oleum Terebinth,</hi> ℥ ſs, of Iuniper berries, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 
                     <hi>ij,</hi> of Cloues, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, Nutmegs, Maces, Ana. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. mixe them with <hi>Oleum Cerae,</hi> q. s. to make it in forme of a liniment, and therewith anoint the parts.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Squinancie cured by <hi>I. P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis medecine following, did helpe one that was ſo ſwolne and grieuouſlie pained, that he could ſcarcelie eate or drinke. ℞ <hi>Olei philoſophorum de lateribus,</hi> ℥ <hi>ij, olei lini,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vj, <hi>olei cerae,</hi> ℥ j, mixe them warme, and anoint the place affected, oftentimes in the day. Alſo one dram of the tooth of a wilde Boare, being drunke with ℥ <hi>iij</hi> of oile of Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, doth helpe it preſently.</p>
               <p>Alſo another man, was forthwith cured thereof, which drunke one ſpoonefull of <hi>Aqua balſami,</hi> and wetting a cloth therein, applied it to his throate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> The cure of Alopecia, by <hi>I.P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAgno licore Fiorauante,</hi> being annointed on the head, cauſeth the haires to grow againe aboundantly, which are falne away, and to waxe black. <hi>Balſamum ſulfuris</hi> alſo doth the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> A gargariſme to purge the head, by <hi>I. S.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke Spikenard, Alizander ſeed, ana ℥ j. beate them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to powder, and boile them in vinegar till halfe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Then ſtraine it, and put thereto <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs of Muſtard,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18630:22"/>
and ℥ <hi>iiij,</hi> of Roſe water, boile it a little, keepe it cloſe to thy vſe, and when you will, you may take a ſpoonfull warme in the morning, and gargle therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The Pinne and Web, cured by <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE tooke an handfull of <hi>Centumpedes,</hi> or Sowes, ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſtrained them with Ale, and gaue the patient to drinke thereof, three or foure mornings, and willed the patient to ſtop his noſe and mouth, and to hang downe his head, and therewith hee was healed, as I was crediblie certified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> A water for ſore eyes, prooued by <hi>M. E.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Gentlewoman with this water hath cured a very great number of ſore eyes. Shee tooke an Egge, hard ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, cut it in the midſt, and tooke forth the yoalke, and put thereto as much white Copperoſe as a Nutte. Then ſhee cloſed it together, and wrapped it in redde Fennell, and laide it to ſteepe foure and twentie houres in Roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then ſhe ſtrained it hard thorow a cloath, and dropped it into the eyes, morning and euening; it was held for a great ſecret.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another maner or vvaie, to heale the Pinne and Webbe in the eyes.</head>
                  <p>TAke nine of the VVormes called <hi>Centumpedes,</hi> or Sowes, ſtampe and ſtraine them, with the iuice of VVoodbine, or Betonie, for three or foure mornings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether warme: which being drunke, will conſume the VVebbe in the eye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18630:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The ſtaying of the bleeding at the noſe, done hy <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke burnt Lome, M ij, ſharpe vinegar, <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs, mixe them well, and lay it betweene a linnen cloth: and binde it to the forehead cold, and in ſhort ſpace it will ſtint.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame. <hi>I. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Man of fiftie yeares of age, had a great fluxe of bloud at the noſethrill, which had continued a long time, and could finde no remedie, till he vſed this order and medicine following. Firſt his ring finger was bound hard with a thred, then was this cataplaſme following, applyed to his forehead and temples.</p>
                  <p>Take burnt lome, made in powder, M vj, ſtrong vineger, as much as will ſuffice, to make it in forme of a Cataplaſme, to be applyed colde, thus in few houres the bloud ſtinted. Neuertheleſſe he tooke morning and euening, the fume of <hi>Succinum album,</hi> at the mouth and noſe: which ſtaied the fluxe: and comforted the vitall and animall ſpirits. His diet was cold and drying, his drinke was water, or red wine, wherein was put <hi>Crocus martis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another kinde of curing the ſame, performed by <hi>D. B.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONe bleeding at the noſe a day and a night, was thus helped. Hee made a tent of lint, and dipped it in Inke, and put it into his noſethrils, and laide a defenſatiue ouer his eyes and noſe, made with <hi>Sanguis draconis, bole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke,</hi> and a little vinegar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another vvay.</head>
                  <p>MAny haue beene cured, by applying vnto their cods, a linnen cloath wet in Vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18630:23"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>SOme haue had the bleeding ſtinted, by applying the herbe <hi>Peruinca</hi> vnto the noſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other waies to do the ſame.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CArduus benedictus</hi> bruſed, and put vp into the noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrils,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſtinteth the bleeding at the noſe. The ſame it performeth in a wound.</p>
                  <p>The herbe <hi>Geranium,</hi> which hath a red ſtalke, being put into the noſethrils or wound, doth the ſame: verie often prooued.</p>
                  <p>In like maner, and to the ſame effect, worketh <hi>Crocus martis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo the bloud of a man dried, worketh after the ſame order: both for the ſtaying of bloud at the noſe, and in a wound.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Spatting of bloud ſtayed, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine woman ſpat bloud three or foure dayes in great quantitie, who was cured by drinking the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of mints in vineger.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>ALſo fiue or ſixe drops of <hi>Oleum Maſtiche,</hi> dronke in Cinamon water, ſtaieth the ſpatting of bloud.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> The falling downe of the Vuula, and the inflamation of the Almonds, in ſuch ſort, that they could not ſwallow their meat, nor fetch their breath well, cured by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke white Amber groſlie beaten <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, and with a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell take the fume thereof caſt on a few coales, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18630:23"/>
noone, and night. Then take ℥ j of old leauen, and ſpred it plaſterwiſe on a cloath, ſtrew thereon a little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min ſeed, and the powder of white Amber, and applie it halfe an hand breadth to the crowne of the head, the ſpace of an whole day, then at night lay on another, and in ſhort time it will take away the ſwelling, often prooued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The cure of the hicket, by <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe that was diuers times grieuouſlie troubled with the Hicquet, was cured, by applying a browne toſt warme to his ſtomack: the toſte was ſteeped in Triacle and <hi>Aquauitae.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>DIuers haue beene cured thereof, by taking foure or fiue graines of <hi>Landanum noſtrum,</hi> in wine or Malmſey.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> The falling ſickneſſe cured, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine woman, being a Barbars wife in Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, which was greeued therewith euery change of the Moone, was preſerued, by taking each day three drops of <hi>Oleum Heraclei.</hi> with the extract of <hi>Peonie.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another performed by <hi>I. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt you ſhall purge them with the extract of <hi>Helleborus niger:</hi> the doſe whereof is from eight graines to twelue, being before well corrected, and then drunke in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient liquor or potion. That done, he gaue them mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening of this compoſition: the which the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that they vſe, the better will it be for them. ℞ <hi>eſſenciae Peoniae,</hi> conſerue of Roſemarie flowres, of Betonie, ana q.v. mixe them together in forme of an electuarie: then adde
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18630:24"/>
thereto, for euery ℥ of that compoſition, of <hi>oleum cranij hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam</hi> ℈ j, and ℈ ſs of oile of Roſemarie flowers, and twelue grames of <hi>oleum vitrioli.</hi> Hereof let them take ℥ ſs, at a time, either by it ſelfe, or with ſome conuenient liquor, broth, or potion. Alſo the nuke of the neck, muſt be anointed with <hi>Oleum caſtorei:</hi> when they do fall, you ſhall anoint their noſethrils with <hi>oleum ſuccinum,</hi> for that will in ſhort time recouer them againe. It will be alſo very expedient to vſe thoſe things that comfort the braine and the heart.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> The cure of the Iaundies, by <hi>I. P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Yong maiden, much affected with them, was in this ſort cured. She was twiſe purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> and as often with <hi>Panchimagogon.</hi> This done, ſhee felt her ſelfe verie much eaſed, ſaue onely in her yellow colour, which was thus alſo taken away. Shee tooke three or foure mornings ℥ iij, of the decoction of Gooſe dung, ℈ ij. of the extract of Centorie, which ſhe drunke warme, and ſo was cured.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Woman that had the yellow Iaundies', aboue two yeares together, was thus cured. Firſt ſhe tooke <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, of <hi>Balſamum artificiale Leon. Fior.</hi> with a ſpoonfull of white wine in the morning: which cauſed her the next day, to be as yellow as Saffron, all her bodie ouer, yea her haire of her head, and the nailes of her hands, and feete, very ſtrange to behold. The third daie, ſhee tooke the ſame againe, and in three times ſhee was perfectlie cured. This was at Carleton, fiue or ſixe miles from Bedford. Certaine practitioners, haue found a great ſecret, in the ſalt called <hi>Lapilli vrinae,</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus</hi> his <hi>Rebiſola,</hi> againſt the Iaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and all obſtructions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18630:24"/>
                  <head>Another way, by the ſame Perſon <hi>VV. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Nucis Cupreſſi, Caſſiae ligni,</hi> ana ℥ j, extract <hi>Centaurij, ℈ ij,</hi> mixe them, and drinke it in white wine warme: and they ſhall after the receit thereof, euacuate in their vrine, great ſtore of yellowiſh choller, but by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this medecine, twiſe or thriſe, it will vade quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, as hath beene often prooued. Remember, that before you take this medecine (that it may worke with better effect) you receiue a doſe or two, of <hi>Aromatico Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of the Iaundies, with obſtruction of the menſtrues, performed by <hi>VV. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Yong Gentlewoman, eighteene yeares old, was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie greeued with the Iaundies and ſuppreſſion of her naturall ſickneſſe: but was in this ſort cured.</p>
                  <p>℞ water of Madder rootes, Sage, and Betonie, ana ℥ iiij, <hi>Spiritus Tartari, ℥ ij, oleum vitrioli, ℈ ij,</hi> mixe them, and drinke therof morning and euening two or three ℥ warme. Alſo you ſhall note, that ſhe was purged once (before ſhee tooke this drinke) with <hi>Arom. Leonardo,</hi> and ſo was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie cured, and had her courſes againe, which before ſhee wanted ſeauen moneths and more.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> The healing and cure of great windineſſe in the ſtomacke by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine Gentleman, who was afflicted with a windi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſtomack, that many times with extreame paine, he fell into a ſound. In this miſerie hee continued three yeares and more, but in this manner hee was holpen. Firſt hee tooke <hi>Aromat. Leon.</hi> which euacuated vpward and downeward, the groſe and viſcous cauſe of this winde. After that hee had vſed this potion following fortie dayes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18630:25"/>
together. He tooke euery morning and euening, <hi>Spiritus tartari,</hi> corrected with his <hi>Criſtaline</hi> ſalt halfe a ſpoonefull, <hi>Aqua preſeruans</hi> as much. This withdrew the cauſe, opened all obſtructions in the bodie, ſo that in a moneth he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perfectly cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Cough of the lungs, cured by <hi>W. T.</hi> after this maner.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REcipe Aquae Marrubij,</hi> ℥ vj, ſirrup of <hi>Iuiubes, ℥ iij,</hi> mixe them, and make thereof a Iulepe: whereof the patient tooke foure ſpoonfuls, with <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j of <hi>Balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> euery foure howres till he was well.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another cured by <hi>W. T.</hi> which had alſo a ſore ſtitch in the ſide.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt he tooke <hi>Aromat. Leon.</hi> and then tooke this potion following, for certaine dayes. ℞ <hi>Carduus Benedictus, Hypericon,</hi> Folefoote, a little <hi>Enula compana,</hi> make thereof a decoction with Ale, and he dranke euery morning <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j of <hi>Balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> and a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aqua Balſami Fiora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uante,</hi> morning and euening, till he was cured.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Shortneſſe of breath, with a cough, remedied by <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt he was purged with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo,</hi> then he vſed this diet, with hote and drying meates, roſte or ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. <hi>Enula campana,</hi> Hiſop, and Liquerice, were infuſed in his wine. Alſo he vſed euery morning, to drinke or eate in a rere Egge. ℈ ſs of <hi>Balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> and thereby was ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and quicklie cured.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18630:25"/>
                  <head>Another remedie for ſhortneſſe of breath.</head>
                  <p>THe wormes called <hi>Centumpedes</hi> or Sowes, are of great vertue, to diſcharge the lungs, that are ſtuffed with groſe fleame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> An approoued remedie to ſlaie vomiting, by <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man of thirtie yeares old, was troubled a long time with ſore vomiting, throwing vp preſently whatſoeuer he ate or dranke, and was thus relieued. ℞. Malmeſey ℥ vj. <hi>Oleum vitrioli,</hi> vj. drops or more, mixe them together, and take thereof euery morning faſting, ℥ j, or there about, and in ſhort time it will ſtay the vomite.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To ſtaie vomiting of bloud.</head>
                  <p>TAke fiue or ſixe drops of oile of Maſtick, and drinke it in Cinamon water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To ſtay vomiting, another waie.</head>
                  <p>A Pultus thus made, as followeth, and applyed to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, ſtaieth vomiting. Take Rie leauen, and mixe it with the iuice of mints, and a little vinegar, ouer the fire, in forme of a pultus, when you do applie it to the ſtomack, ſtrew thereon the powder of Cloues, and ſo oft as it cooleth applie it warme. Alſo a Rie toſte ſtieped in vinegar, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the ſtomack.</p>
                  <p>The oile of Wormwood (that commeth by diſtillation) being drunke with conuenient liquors, or potions, and the ſame compounded with other conuenient things, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the ſtomack, doth worke notable effect this way, and is good againſt manie other maladies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:18630:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Vomiting of bloud, with a cruell fluxe of the bellie, ſtaied by <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man 45 yeares old, that had congeled bloud in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, did vomite aboundance of bloud, and auoided downward a certaine blacke matter like vnto pitche. He had a great ſtitch in his ſide, without a feauer: and alwaies when he vomited, it was thought he would haue died, this man was by Gods helpe thus cured. Firſt hee tooke this potion. Take the water of Nettle rootes ℥ viij, <hi>Oleum vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oli,</hi> as much as will make it tart. He dranke thereof cold, which preſently mitigated both the fluxes. Then vnto the ſtomack and throate, was applyed this pultus warme, both morning and euening, which wrought an excellent effect. ℞. the crummes of Rie bread, M xij, Red wine or Aligant, ſtrong Vinegar, <hi>ana</hi> q. s. boile them to the forme of a pultus. Then hee tooke at the mouth and noſe, the ſume of <hi>Succinum</hi> or Amber, which ſtrengthened the vitall and animall ſpirits. His ſide was annointed with this oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which tooke away the pricking and paine. ℞. <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. de Althea,</hi> ℥ 4, <hi>amigdalarum dulcium,</hi> ℥ j, mixe them, and therewith annoint the ſide, morning and euening. His diet was this, all his meate was boiled in Red wine, or Smithes water. His drinke was the decoction of Nettle rootes, or Red Wine, wherein Steele had beene quenched diuerſe times.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vomiting ioyned with a Feauer.</head>
                  <p>A Gentlewoman affected with theſe greefes, was in this manner comforted. ℞. <hi>Aquae balſami,</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, <hi>Aquae pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeru. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij, oleum piperis,</hi> Graines vj, mixe them well with a good ſpoonfull of the ſirupe of Quinces, and ſo ſhe dranke it, at the beginning of the heate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18630:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> A great and ſore pluriſie cured, by <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine man of xxiiij. yeares old was vexed with a moſt greeuous pluriſie, with pricking, ſhooting, and a cough, with a continuall feauer, and inflammation of the tongue. Firſt, there was good ſtore of bloud taken from the liuer vaine, on that ſide where the paine was. Then were theſe ſirups (that do decoct and purge) miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. ℞. <hi>Syrupi de liquericia, de Hyſopo, acetoſae ana</hi> ℥ j, <hi>Oximellitis ſquillitici, aceti ſquillitici, ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij, make thereof a loche, whereof in the morning he licked with a Liquorice ſtick, which cauſed him to ſpatte eaſilie, and tooke away the heate or burning of the tongue, being vſed with this decoction. ℞. French Barlie, ℥ iij, <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> M j, Roſes, Violets, <hi>ana</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr> j, Licorice ſcraped, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij, Figs iij, Raiſin, ℥ j ſs, Sugar Candie, ℥ ij, boile them in xvi. <abbr>lb.</abbr> of water, till two pound be waſted, and ſo drinke it colde. Alſo his diet was light and thinne, as broth and drinke, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pluriſie, with ſpatting of bloud, cured by <hi>M. R.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt there was made this purging preparatiue. ℞. <hi>Senae</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vj, <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> M ſs. Sugar, ℥ ſs. Ginger, ℥ ſs, laie them to infuſe one night in warme whaie, made of Goates milke, <abbr>lb</abbr> j ſs, whereof yee ſhall giue morning and euening, ℥ iiij warme: this purgeth gentlie, and cauſeth to ſpat eaſilie. Then three daies after, they muſt bleed well on the liuer vaine, and their drinke at meales, was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of hyſop, violets, liquerice, and raiſins with ſugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pluriſie, with inflammation of the tongue, and coſtiueneſſe of the bodie. <hi>M. R.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt they were purged with <hi>Aromatico,</hi> and then vſed this gargariſme. ℞. <hi>Semperuiue,</hi> or howſleeke, M ij, boile them in a quart of water, till a third be waſted. Then ſtraine it,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18630:27"/>
and put thereto ℥ <hi>ij</hi> of wine vinegar, wherewith they gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſed warme oftentimes. Then they vſed <hi>Mel roſarum,</hi> which tooke away the blackneſſe of the toung. Their diet was moiſt and cooling as followeth. ℞. French Barlie ℥ ſs, Figs vij. Raiſens ℥ iiij, boile and ſtraine them, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>oleum vitrioli,</hi> q. s. to make it tart, and ſo drinke thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pluriſie in a woman cured.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt ſhe was purged with <hi>Arom. Leonardo,</hi> then vnto her ſide there was applyed this vnguent, ſeauen or eight times a day, which tooke away her paine, ℞. <hi>vnguenti de Althea,</hi> ℥ <hi>ij,</hi> oile of ſweete Almonds, ℥ ſs. mixe them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the next morning ſhee was let bloud in the baſilike vaine, on that ſide where her paine was. Her diet was the ſame that was ſpoken of before. After meate, ſhee vſed a <hi>Lochſanum</hi> ſit for the purpoſe, and ſo in ſhort time ſhe was cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another woman cured of the ſame diſeaſe, by <hi>M.R.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt there was miniſtred vnto her this potion, ℞. the water of <hi>Carduus benedictus,</hi> 
                     <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs, <hi>Oleum vitrioli,</hi> q. s. to make it tarte like a Pomegranate. The next day ſhe was let bloud in maner aforeſaid, about ℥ x. After ſhe had bled, ſhe tooke this potion following, fiue daies together, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening: which cauſed her to ſweate well, and thereupon ſhe was quicklie cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Diaphoreticall decoction.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe, Cardui Benedicti,</hi> M <hi>ij,</hi> liquorice ſcraped, ℥ iij, figs v. Raiſens ℥ <hi>ij,</hi> ſugar candie, ℥ i ſs, boile them in a ſufficient quantitie of water, and ſtraine them to drinke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A pluriſie broken with a potion.</head>
                  <p>FOr the breaking of his Apoſteme, there was miniſtred vnto him <hi>Aromatico Leonardo,</hi> with honied water. The next day, the baſilicke vaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Pleuciticall</hi> ſide was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18630:27"/>
opened. His drinke at dinner and ſupper was this decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Take Iſope dried, M j, Violets, P ij, ſixe Figs, liquerice ſcraped, ℥ ſs, Raiſens ℥ iiij, boile them in ix. pound of water till one pound be waſted, then ſtraine this pectorall decoction, and vſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another cured in this manner.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt he tooke <hi>Aromatico Leon.</hi> and therevpon dranke the water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus.</hi> The next day, they let him bloud on the ſame ſide where the paine was. His diet was moiſt and cooling, and he dranke Barlie water, mixed with ſirupe of Roſes, and <hi>oleum vitrioli,</hi> and ſhortly after was cured.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> An inward impoſtume, or baſtard pluriſie, cured by <hi>W. M.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man hauing an impoſtume in his ſide, which would haue turned to the pluriſie, was thus cured. Take a good ſweete Apple, and cut off the crowne, take out the core, and fill it with powder' of <hi>Olibanum,</hi> binde on the crowne againe, and roſte it vnder the embers, till it be ſoft. Then mixe with it three or foure drops of <hi>Oleum vitrioli,</hi> and let the patient eate it, and ſweat thereon.</p>
               <p>Alſo with the ſame medicine, at the ſame time, there was a boye helped, that had a plague ſore on his neck.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Paine in the ſide with a cough, cured by <hi>W.T.</hi> after this manner.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe, Floris Sulphuris, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij.</hi> the extract of <hi>Enula Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana,</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, Ireos and Liquorice, <hi>ana</hi> ℥ j. honie, q. s. to make it in forme of an electuarie. Before it be made vp, put thereto, ℈ ſs, of <hi>Oleum ſulfuris,</hi> and vſe it morning and euening.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18630:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Paine and winde in the bodie, cured by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine woman 28. yeares of age, being often trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a griping paine and winde in her bodie, was preſently eaſed, by taking foure or fiue graines of <hi>Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num noſtrum</hi> in Malmeſey, with two or three drops of oile of Aniſeeds. After this manner, diuerſe perſons haue beene cured. Prouided alwaies that the bodie be looſe, elſe muſt it be mooued, either with ſome gentle cliſter or ſuppoſitarie.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The expelling of winde out of the bodie, by <hi>L. F.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis courſe following, hath beene diuerſe times proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued moſt effectuall, againſt winde in the ſtomack, and other parts of the bodie. Firſt let them take a doſe of <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. Leonardo.</hi> Then let them take morning and euening, halfe a dream of this compoſition, three or foure daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, either in potion or pilles.</p>
                  <p>℞. the eſſence of <hi>Gentian, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij,</hi> the eſſence of Ginger, oile of Aniſeed, Fennell ſeed, <hi>ana</hi> ℈ ſs, make thereof a maſſe, and keepe it to your vſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> The cure of the Dropſie, performed by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man of three and fortie yeares old; troubled with the Dropſie, was in this manner cured. Take the rootes of blew Flower de Lilce, ſliced, and ſteeped in vinegar, three or foure houres, and then dried, ℥ ſs, the barke of Laurell rootes, ſo prepared, as much; the leaues of Sena, in pouder, one ſpoonfull, Aniſeed, and Ginger, <hi>ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i, mixe them, and take of that pouder euerie morning, from the waight of foure pence, till it giue you foure ſtooles a daie, continue herein ſo long, as you ſhall thinke it good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18630:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII</hi> The killing and expelling of wormes in the ſtomacke or elſewhere, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN infinite number of people, both young and old, haue beene cured thereof, with this compoſition following. Take the ſeed of <hi>Carduus ſanctus,</hi> Wormeſeed, Dittanie, <hi>Semen Caulium, cornucerui vſti, coralline, vermium terreſtrium, ana</hi> ℥ ſs, mixe them in fine pouder, and giue thereof <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with honie, or ſweete milke, in the morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Anoint alſo the ſtomack, and bellie downward, with this vnguent following, and applie a little vnto the nauell, with browne paper, and no doubt of it, within two or three daies, the patient ſhalbe cured. For it doth not onely kill the wormes, but cauſeth them to come forth by ſiege, making the bellie ſoluble, ſo that they ſhall haue two or three ſtooles in a day. The <hi>cataplaſme</hi> or <hi>vnguent</hi> is this. ℞. <hi>Farinae lupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, Aloes, centauriae, myrrhae, theriacae optimae, ana</hi> ℥ ſs, beat them into fine pouder, and make thereof an vnguent, with the iuice of peach leaues, and keepe it to your vſe. Alſo two or three drops of <hi>Oleum vitrioli,</hi> being dronke with water of gramen, or ſuch like, for three or foure daies, killeth wormes. Alſo <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 
                  <hi>ij,</hi> of <hi>Quinteſſencia ſolutiuo Phiorau.</hi> dronke with ℥ j, of ſirupe of Roſes, killeth the wormes, and expelleth them by ſiege.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIIII.</hi> A quartaine of long continuance, cured by <hi>L. F.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt the patient was purged, with 12. graines of <hi>La petra Philoſophale, Leon. Phiorau.</hi> mixed with <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs of good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridate, the next day he tooke of this decoction warme, ℥ vj, and ſo continued 14 daies, morning and euening. ℞. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mepiteos</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr> j, white wine <abbr>lb</abbr> viij. white honie <abbr>lb</abbr> j, diſtill them with a gentle fire, till fiue pound be come forth. Then let it coole, and filter that which remained in the veſſel, &amp; mixe it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18630:29"/>
with that which was diſtilled afore, keepe it in a glaſſe, cloſe ſtopped, and vſe it. Alſo the raines of the backe, was anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euery night with <hi>Balſamum artific. Leon. Phior.</hi> and ſo he was well cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> An approoued remedie against the peſtilence, pluriſie, and quartaine.</head>
               <p>DIuers people haue beene cured of theſe foreſaid diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by taking a doſe of <hi>Turpetum Diaphoreticum, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raceli,</hi> either with <hi>Amuletum Palmarij,</hi> or with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent good Mithridate, in the morning faſting, and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therevpon. Sometime it is giuen with other potions or compoſitions, according to the diſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> The ſwelling of the ſpleene, in a melancholick perſon, cured by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine melancholie man, was much grieued in his milt, heart, and head: but he was thus cured. Firſt he was twice purged, with ℈ j. of <hi>Panchimagogon,</hi> and one ℈ of the extract of <hi>Sena,</hi> mixed with ſirupe or Roſes, and two or three drops of oile of vitrioll. That done, he tooke a quart of poſſet Ale, made of white wine and Burnet, and dranke thereof, morning, noone, and night, a good draught, with halfe a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aqua Balſami Fiorauan.</hi> Alſo now and then, he tooke morning and euening, a toſte of white bread, ſtieped in <hi>Aquam Preſeruans,</hi> and within ten daies after, he purged againe, and ſo remained in good health.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> Franticke feauers, for want of ſleepe, often cured by <hi>I. P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny that were ſo greeuouſlie vexed, with a burning feauer, that they could not ſleepe, and were in maner
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18630:29"/>
frantick, haue taken fiue or ſixe graines of <hi>Laudanum,</hi> with conſerue of ſuccorie flowres, and therewith were ſpeedily deliuered out of their extremities.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Peſtilent feauers, with great thirſt cured, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt they were purged once or twiſe with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo:</hi> then was the ſtomack comforted with ſome pectorall potion. That being done, there was Barlie water made with raiſons, licorice, and coole herbes, if you may haue them. Then ſtraine it cleane, and put therein as much <hi>Oleum vitrioli</hi> as will make it tarte, like a Pomegranate, Drinke thereof when you are drie, for it comforteth nature, ſwageth heate and thirſt wonderfullie, openeth all obſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and defendeth the bodie from putrified feauers. If they be greeued with the headache, you ſhall cauſe them to be let bloud vnder the toung, cutting thoſe vaines ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart, and they ſhall preſently be cured.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> Againſt poiſon, or the Peſtilence, a diaphoreticall potion, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REcipe <hi>Mirrhae, croci, ana ℥ ij, Amuleti Palmarij</hi> ℥ j, <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus vini</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb</abbr> j, <hi>Oleum piperis, Oleum gingiberis, ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, mixe them in a glaſſe, and giue thereof ℥ ſs in old Sack at once, againſt the peſtilence or poiſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> Signes of death in the Plague. <hi>W. K.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a quick Frog, and lay it with the bellie next the ſore: if the partie will eſcape, the Frog will burſt, in a quarter of an houre. Then lay on another, and this you ſhall do, till no more do burſt, for they draw forth the venome. I haue beene told that a dried tode will in better ſort do the ſame. If none of the Frogs do burſt, the partie will not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18630:30"/>
eſcape, this hath bene often prooued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Counſell, antidotes, and preſeruatiues, againſt infectious aires, on the water, or land, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu ſhall vſe to chew, or hold in your mouth, a little of <hi>Eſſentia Angelicae.</hi> Alſo it would be verie profitable to drinke three or fowre droppes of the ſame faſting. Alſo <hi>Oleum Camphorae</hi> being dronke, effecteth the ſame. In like maner, <hi>aqua balſami Phiorauante,</hi> if it be dronke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with wine, or Allome, preſerueth a man from all poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and peſtilent aires: and is a moſt ſingular remedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſurfets, or the peſtilence. Alſo, if you be in any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſhip, or houſe, it were neceſſarie to weare a bag of Saffron vnder your arme pits to defend the heart.</p>
               <p>Alſo it were very neceſſary, to drinke two or three drops, of the eſſence of ſaffron, for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amuletum Palmarij,</hi> is alſo verie excellent, being taken in the morning faſting.</p>
               <p>Diſſolued pearle, eaten or dronke, defendeth the hart pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth the bloud, and reuiueth the ſpirites aboue all other things. You may make it in lozinges, or drink it in any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall, in what quantitie you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> An inueterate Gonorrhaea, either in man or woman, oftentimes cured, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny haue bene cured of this, and ſuch like infirmities, with this compoſition following. Among the reſt, one Gentleman in Buckinghamſhire, who was vexed therewith, aboue ſeuen yeares continually.</p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman alſo, was ſo greeuouſlie afflicted with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18630:30"/>
                  <hi>ſlux. albo,</hi> that ſhe waxed lame, and went with a ſtaffe: theſe were both cured in 12. dayes. But one thing muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that if it come <hi>ex lue venerea,</hi> it were neceſſarie, firſt to be purged, and then to vſe theſe pilles.</p>
               <p>℞. <hi>magisterij perlarum,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, <hi>Gumme Tragacanth,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, fine bole Armeniack, <hi>terra ſigillata vera, ana.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>Laudanum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> ℈ j, make an hard maſſe, with Turpentine, and take thereof, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, when you go to bed, vntill this quantitie be ſpent. In the meane time alſo, you ſhall annoint the reines of the backe, with this vnguent.</p>
               <p>℞. <hi>vnguentum album camphoratum, ℥ ij, ſaccarum Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij, miſce, fiat vnguentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An other for the ſame. <hi>W. T.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt purge them with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo,</hi> once or twiſe, then let them take, morning and euening, halfe a dramme of the pilles following: and annoint the reines of the backe, with the foreſaid vnguent.</p>
                  <p>℞. <hi>Symphyti, craſſulae, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij. Magiſterij perlarum,</hi> diſſolued corall, <hi>ana</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, <hi>Laudani nostri,</hi> ℈ j, <hi>nucis moſchatae, numero ij, boli Armen. terrae ſigillatae verae ſem. papau, albi, Tragacanth. ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij,</hi> make them vp in a maſſe, with Turpentine and vſe them in manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An electuarie againſt Gonorrhaea, by <hi>W.</hi> T.</head>
                  <p>A Certaine man, being troubled with a ſtinking <hi>Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaea,</hi> was in this order cured. Firſt he was purged with <hi>Aromatico Leonardo:</hi> the next day, he tooke a pill or two, of Venice Turpentine, waſhed in plantaine water, That done, he vſed to eate morning and euening, the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of an hazell nut, of this electuarie, vntill he was helped which was not long after.</p>
                  <p>Take the kernels of hazell nuttes, blaunched, ℥ iiij,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18630:31"/>
                     <hi>magiſterij perlarum, laudani noſtri, ana ℈ j, terrae ſigillatae, boli, veri, ſanginnis draconis</hi> in graine, <hi>ana ℈ ij, Seminis Plautaginis, raſurae Eboris, ana</hi> ℈ j, <hi>nucis moſchatae.</hi> 3. or 4. <hi>Cinamomi,</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, <hi>Saccari,</hi> ℥ iij. mixe them well together, and vſe it. Alſo in the meane time, he annointed the raines with the foreſaid vnguent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> The immoderate ſluxe menſtruall, ſuppreſſed or ſtared, by <hi>W. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine woman, being greeuouſlie weakened with that diſeaſe, and hauing great heate and paine in her bodie, was thus cured. Take the rootes of Orpine, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferie, thinne ſliced, Clarey q. v. boile them with a chicken, and with that broth make Almond milke, and to euerie handfull of Almondes, adde one ℈ of <hi>Laudanum noſtrum,</hi> Grinde them well together, and drinke thereof morning and euening. Alſo you ſhall anoint the raines and greeued parts, with the vnguent mentioned in the Chapter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another againſt the ſame.</head>
                  <p>I Was informed, that the powder of a land Frog, bound about the womans neck, doth ſtay the foreſaid fluxe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> A Fluxe ſtopped by <hi>G. F.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DIſſolue Baie ſalt in Malmeſey, and therewith waſh the ſoles of your feete, and in three or foure dayes it will ſtaie the Fluxe. Diuerſe Souldiars in the warres haue beene cured thereof, by ſetting their fundament in warme Horſe dung. Alſo the pouder of red Roſes, dronke in Red wine, is verie profitable for the ſtopping of the Fluxe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18630:31"/>
                  <head>Bloudie Fluxe of long continuance, cured by <hi>W. T.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REcipe, conſerue of red Roſes, Marmilade of quinces, electuarie of Sulphur, of <hi>Leon. Fiorau.</hi> his deſcription, <hi>ana ℥ ij, Amuletum Palmarij,</hi> ℥ ſs, <hi>eſſentiae croci, Laudanum noſtrum, ana</hi> ℈ ſs, <hi>aquae preſeruantis,</hi> ℥ ſs, <hi>oleum vitrioli, &amp; ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furis, ana</hi> ℈ ſs, mixe them, and take thereof, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, morning and euening.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIIII.</hi> The cure of the Hemerrhoides or Piles, performed by <hi>I. H.</hi> And many other.</head>
               <p>TAke Mullen, and frie it with Butter, and therewith an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the part diuers times.</p>
               <p>The oile of Egges is a notable remedie, to withdrawe the ſaid infirmitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Balſamum ſulfuris,</hi> anointed vpon them, doth with great ſpeed and good ſucceſſe, cure them: this alſo hath beene oftentimes prooued very excellent.</p>
               <p>If they be anointed with <hi>Oleum Tartari faetens,</hi> it drieth them vp in ſhort time. But firſt it were neceſſarie, to purge the bodie of the melancholike originall of that diſeaſe, both by vomit and ſiege.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to take them away, by applying a cauſtick vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of Ficus in ano, ex lue venerea, performed by <hi>I. P.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MAny haue beene ſore troubled with warts or blathers in the fundament, which haue in verie ſhort time beene cured, by anointing them with <hi>Balſamum Tartari faetens.</hi> Among other men, there was a ſtrong luſtie fellow fiftie yeares old, of complexion melancholike, which was beaſtly beraied with the Pockes, about whoſe fundament, or <hi>Longanon,</hi> there remained 14 or 12 growing, whereof
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18630:32"/>
ſome were ſo big as a little ſigge, all of them did runne or yeeld, a lothſome yellow ſanies or matter. This man was cured, with <hi>Balſamum Tartari foetens:</hi> without any payne to him and the warts were ſo dried, that they were pulled of, with a payre of mullets: after which he remained whole. This man was healed in Bedfordſhire.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> The prouoking of menſtrues, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY this compoſition following, many more then it is here requiſite to ſpeake of, haue had their menſtrues prouoked, and many other obſtructions opened: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it be giuen with brothes, liquors, or medicaments, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate thereunto.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>extractionem Chamomillae, Calendulae, Gentianae, Brio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, Chamepitcos, Paeoniae, Centaurij, Iuniperi, Geniſtae, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binae, Spicaenardi, Rutae, Meliſſae, Chelidoniae, Philipendulae, Matricariae, ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>Eſſentiae Zedoariae, Croci, ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs, <hi>Mirabolanorum, Caſtorei, ana</hi> ℥ ſs, mixe them, and keepe it cloſe. The doſe is from ℈ j, to <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, vpon extremitie, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in pilles or conuenient electuaries. It muſt be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred foure or fiue dayes before the new Moone, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie after, with the infuſion of <hi>Sena,</hi> or in ſirupe of roſes, for the intent aboue named.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To prouoke menstrues, in melancholike people. <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke of the extract of <hi>Helleborus niger,</hi> fiue graynes, <hi>Panchimagogon</hi> 15. graynes, make it into three ſmall pilles, and annoint the pilles, with <hi>Oleum aniſi,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of take once or twiſe. After that take this compoſition fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <p>Take of the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Gentian, Sabinae, Angelica,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18630:32"/>
ana</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, <hi>Eſſencia Croci, ℈ j, Caſtorei</hi> ℈ ſs, mixe them, and make them vp in forme of pilles, and take thereof ech night, when you go to bed, ℈ j, either in pilles, or diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſome conuenient liquor, about the foreſaid time of the Moone. A verie melancholike maiden, was cured in this manner.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> Suffocation and paynes of the Matrix, with retention of menſtrues, cured, by <hi>I. P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REcipe extract. Brioniae,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j ſs, the leaues of <hi>Sena,</hi> ℥ ſs, gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ℈ j, Cinamon, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, ſuger, ℥ j, lay them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe one night, in a pint of warme whay, made of goats milke. Then ſtrayne it, and drinke thereof three mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings warme, about the new Moone; keeping a warme and drying diet, your wine muſt be infuſed with roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie flowres.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another that hath cured, the riſing of the mother, by <hi>R. C.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe</hi> the flowres or buds of a walnut tree, in May, giue the patients as much thereof to drinke, as wil lye on a groat, and with two or three doſes they ſhall be cured.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if you giue. ℈ j, of <hi>oleum ſuccinum album,</hi> in wine, it will preſently cure the ſame diſeaſe, a thing oftentimes proued with good ſucceſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> To prouoke vrine, and to cauſe the Iaundies to flow. <hi>W. K.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe powder of earth wormes, dronke with white wine, pouoketh vrine and cureth the Iaundies and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</p>
               <p>Alſo gray ſope, ℥ ij. bay ſalt, finely beaten, ℥ j, mixe them, and therewith annoint the nauell, and bellie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18630:33"/>Alſo Caſtile Sope being drunke, with warme wine, prouoketh Vrine.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if you ſhall applie quick earth-wormes, vpon a whit blow, called <hi>Panaricium</hi> (of ſome <hi>Panaricies</hi>) they will cure the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> To prouoke Vrine, and to heale other obſtructions, a moſt excellent, and procued receit, by <hi>I. H.</hi> and many other.</head>
               <p>THis compoſition of artificiall ſalts, breaketh, and (after a ſort) conſumeth all tartarous diſeaſes, as hath beene verie often and trulie experimented by diuerſe and ſundrie perſons: yea it preuaileth much againſt the Gowte, being taken with potions, electuaries, and ſirrups, appropriate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the particular miniſtrations.</p>
               <p>℞ the ſalt of Radiſh, of <hi>Eringus,</hi> Beane ſtalkes, Broome, Alizanders, Iuniper, Aſhe, Aniſeed, Fennell, Camomill, VVormwood, Vrine, <hi>Tartar Chriſtalline, ana,</hi> mixe them in a warme morter, and keepe it cloſe, and in a drie place, for in the aire and moiſture it will quickly reſolue. The doſe heereof, is from halfe a ſcruple, to an whole ſcruple, and may be verie ſafelie adminiſtred, without perill, to any age or ſexe: vpon good occaſions, and at times conuenient, after that the bodie it prepared for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The end of the ſecond part of this
Collection.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18630:33"/>
            <head>A SVPPLEMENT, OR ADDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, VNTO THE FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MER COLLECTION.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>This Appendix or Addition, containeth both Philoſophicall diſcourſes, of the cauſes and cures, of diuers and ſundrie diſeaſes: as alſo many pithie diſcourſes, of the vertues and vſe, of many vegetables, animals, &amp;c. culled and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, out of the Phiſickes and Chirurgerie, of S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardo Fiorauante, and left to paſſe ſorth in Print, with this Collection.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of payne in the head.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He paine in the head, is an infirmitie, whoſe cauſe vntill this time hath not beene ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as by mine owne experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I ſhall proue vnto you.</p>
                  <p>All or the moſt part of Phiſicions, in the world, do hold this poſition, that payne in the head, is no other thing, then vapors ariſing from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke: and aſcend vnto the head, which do offend <hi>membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> whereupon enſueth payne. Herein they ſpeake ſome part of the truth. But (in my iudgement) they are not yet come perfectly, to know all the cauſe of this infirmitie. For I ſee that in the cures, which theſe Theorickes wold per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, it falleth not out, according to their expectation and deſire, for that they know not the whole or the principall cauſe of the maladie, therefore what certaine medecine can they finde out to cure the infirmitie? They may percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (as the blind man hits the crow) helpe, they know not what, which thing I ſpeake not, to backbite or iniurie any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18630:34"/>
but to tell them of loue that I beare to them and others, the whole and true cauſe of that, whereof heretofore they haue bene ignoraunt. The firſt cauſe is putrified bloud, in <hi>Leonichie,</hi> the ſecond is, the vapors that aſcend from the ſtomacke and offend the head: the third is, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miditie or moiſture, betweene the skinne and the fleſh. So that the cauſes are three, and the remedies as many, to diſſolue the <hi>antecedent</hi> cauſes. I haue now ſhewed thee, the originall and roote of the payne in the head; about which thou ſhalt neuer more neede to beate thy head, or breake thy braines, either in ſeeking the <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> the <hi>Commentarie</hi> of <hi>Galene,</hi> or the authoritie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicene:</hi> for in theſe foure or few wordes I haue ſaid all. Now of the cure of this diſeaſe, as I haue experimented the ſame an infinite ſort of times in my life: which way ſoeuer the cauſe commeth, worke thou after this manner, and thou ſhalt neuer ſuſtaine blame, or diſcredit.</p>
                  <p>When the payne in the head is confirmed, and that thou canſt finde no helpe, by common <hi>Theorick</hi> or <hi>Practike,</hi> do theſe things following. Firſt let them bloud on <hi>Leonichie,</hi> cutting it ouerthwart, and let the patient ſpat as much as he can. Then the next morning, let them take our <hi>Aromatico</hi> faſting. The next day let the head be ſhauen, and lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an attractiue plaiſter, drawing out the humiditie: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue made mention in my <hi>Caprici medicinale.</hi> In the end, cauſe them to neeſe, and hereby all the payne in the head will ceaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Catarrhe, and rume in the head.</head>
                  <p>THe Catarrhe, is a moiſt vapor, which aſſaulteth the head, and afterward falleth downe agayne, into the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke: where it ingroſſeth and corrupteth. This moiſture, hath his beginning of the moiſture of the lungs, and vntill ſuch time, as the lungs be diſcharged thereof, the Catarrhe will continue in his force. This infirmitie raigneth more in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18630:34"/>
flegmaticke, and melancholike bodies, then in any of other conſtitutions. Such as are troubled with it, are not long li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe their lungs conſume, by little and little, and thereupon they are troubled with the <hi>Ptiſicke:</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently they periſh, if they be not quickly releeued. I will now ſhew thee a rare ſecret to cure the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Take <hi>Pulmonaria</hi> and <hi>Sena,</hi> that is freſh, and new; infuſe them in wine and water, ouer a ſmall or gentle fire, till the wine haue drawne out the vertue. Then ſtraine it, and put thereunto our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> &amp; keepe it cloſe in a glaſſe, let the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t drinke thereof euery morning ℥ iij, luke warme, for twentie dayes together: let him eate good nouriſhing meates, for they agree well with this diſeaſe. If the patient be not too farre ſpent, you ſhall ſee your cure performed in ſhort time. In the meane while, if the patient be weake, you ſhall giue him new layd egges, and good white wine. If the humiditie be perceiued, not to be quite expelled and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacuated, then giue him our <hi>Aromatico:</hi> afterward comfort him agayne, with reſtoratiues and cordials, to make him ſtrong, and no doubt by the helpe of God he ſhall be cured. This methode, of curing this infirmitie, differeth from the common courſe that Phiſitians take, which would cure it, with diet, bleeding, and mollifying liniments, and cauſing them to ſpat, and ſuch like, which are meanes rather to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Catarrhe, then to diminiſh the ſame.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The ſecond courſe, to cure the deſcenſion: that commeth from the head to the ſtomacke.</head>
                     <p>VSe theſe fiue things if you will cure this diſeaſe: firſt our <hi>Electuario Angelica,</hi> 2 <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> 3 our <hi>pillulae pro deſcenſo,</hi> 4 <hi>Vnguents for the ſtomacke and head,</hi> 5 <hi>our Quintaeſſence vegetable.</hi> The electuarie clenſeth the head and ſtomacke, the <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue</hi> euacuateth the body, the pilles take away the cauſe of the deſcenſion: the vnguents drie, and the vegetable <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18630:35"/>
the body from all ill and noiſome infirmities. The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie muſt be taken firſt in the morning: of the <hi>Quinta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence ſolutiue,</hi> you muſt take a ſpoonfull, in the morning, in a little broth and ſuger keeping a reaſonable good diet: and do this foure or ſix dayes. Then take the pilles in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in the meane time, annoint the head and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, with <hi>Oleum cerae,</hi> and drinke euery morning, a little of our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> which if you do vſe continually (by the bleſſing of God vpon it) there is no doubt, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall be free from many troubleſome maladies.</p>
                     <p>There was a certaine woman, of the age of 58. yeares, who being greatly troubled, with a Catarrhe: was cured by the vſe of our <hi>Aqua preſeruans,</hi> morning and euening, and by annointing the ſtomacke with <hi>balſamo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>One that was affected with a <hi>Catarrhe,</hi> and a ſtitch in the ſide, was thus cured. He tooke our <hi>Aromatico</hi> twiſe. Then he tooke euery morning a ſpoonfull of our <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> with the broth of a capon for ſeuen or eight dayes together: and euery night when he went to bed, he annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſtomacke, with <hi>oleum incompoſtibile,</hi> and thereby was ſoone after cured.</p>
                     <p>A woman that had great payne in her head and ſtomack, and had her menſtrues ſtopped; with loſſe of her appetite, was thus helped.</p>
                     <p>Firſt ſhe tooke two doſes of our <hi>Pillulae Angelica,</hi> that done ſhe tooke euery morning, a ſpoonfull of <hi>Quintaeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia ſolurtuo,</hi> with broth and ſuger, for fiue or ſixe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together. After that, ſhe tooke euery morning, one ſpoonfull of our <hi>Aqua preſeruans:</hi> whereupon in ſhort time after ſhe was cured.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A contuſion in the head.</head>
                     <p>A Certaine man, had a great fall from an horſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he bruiſed his head moſt greeuouſly, who was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in foure dayes; by annointing the place, with <hi>Oleum benedictum noſtrum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:18630:35"/>
                     <head>The taking away, or healing of the white ſcall.</head>
                     <p>THis noyſome maladie, is perfectly cured, by purging the patients with our <hi>Aromatico,</hi> and annointing the head with our <hi>Oleum Philoſophorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo the <hi>Artificiall balſame</hi> of our deſcription: doth the like, and <hi>Oleum benedictum noſtrum</hi> effecteth the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Payne in the eyes with great dimneſſe of ſight.</head>
                     <p>A Certaine man that had great payne in his eyes, and was almoſt blind, recouered his ſight; by letting bloud, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the toung. The next day he tooke <hi>Aromatico</hi> once: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he vſed our <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> ſeuen or eight dayes together, and euery night he annointed his ſtomacke, with <hi>Oleum cerae</hi> rectified: then was dropped into his eyes, our <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> for the eyes, and thereof was he well cured.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>An vnguent for ſore eyes.</head>
                     <p>TAke roſe water, fenell, and cufrage water, <hi>ana,</hi> put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſmall quantitie of Verdi grece: &amp; boile it a little on the fire. Then let it ſettle, till it be cleare, and powre it of. With this water, ſee that you waſh <hi>Anxungia porcinae</hi> ſeuen or eight times: and of that, put a little into the eye, when ye go to bed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To cure or ſtay the ſpatting of bloud.</head>
                     <p>ONe that ſpat bloud, was cured in ten dayes, by drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the liquour of honie, morning and euening. An other was healed by drinking the decoctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mint in vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, another by drinking of <hi>Crocus martis.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The deſcription and cure of the Squinancie.</head>
                     <p>THis diſeaſe, is a windie moiſture, and a ſuffocation of bloud, as you may ſee by experience, that ſuch as are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed therewith, haue a great alteration, or many chaunges
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18630:36"/>
of feuers; with a ſwelling in the throte: and many times if it be not quickly holpen, it will choke them, and this is the cure thereof. You ſhall giue them <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, of the powder of a wild Bores tooth, with ℥ iij, of oyle of linſeede, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by the helpe of God they ſhalbe greatly eaſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The deſcription and manifold cures, of the diſeaſe called Scrophulae, or for unculi, which ſome do call waxing kernels, but rather the kings euill.</head>
                     <p>THe <hi>Scrophulae</hi> or waxing kernels (ſo called of ſome) which vſe to come in the throte, or other partes of the bodies, of young children, do ariſe and are cauſed, of great quantitie of melancholike humors, becauſe that doth for the moſt part raigne in perſons, that are weake of comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion. For you may eaſily ſee that ſuch as are vexed with that infirmitie: are not very quicke ſpirited. Theſe <hi>Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulae,</hi> are a long time ere they will come to ſuppuration: and before they breake, and when they are broken, they cauſe exceſſiue payne, and are hard to be cured. For all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities that come of melancholie, are troubleſome to cure or reſolue, as you may ſee in the quartaine and ſuch like. But here I will ſhew thee a ſecret, to cure theſe <hi>Scrophulae.</hi> Firſt you muſt remoue the cauſe, and then cure the effectes: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it were impoſſible to cure them with outward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines. This melancholie is purged, with our ſirupe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt melancholie, which you muſt vſe eight or ten dayes. The doſe is about ℥ 4 cold. That done giue them our <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matico,</hi> which clenſeth the head, and ſtomacke, and purifieth the bloud. As touching locall medicines, to breake it, you ſhall lay thereon our cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 24. houres: which mortifieth and drieth, for it will dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> a great deale of moiſture. After this, annoint it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>agno licore,</hi> vntill the eſcare be fallen out: and when it is mundified, applie thereon the <hi>cerote</hi> of <hi>Gualtifredo di Medi,</hi> &amp; vſe no other medecine, for it will incarnate, and cicatriſe, without ſcare.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18630:36"/>
                     <head>Another cure for Scrophulae.</head>
                     <p>A Certaine young boy of 14. yeares, of complexion cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke, and melancholicke, who had <hi>Scrophulae</hi> in his throte, on both the ſides, was cured thus. The firſt mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine that he tooke, was the infuſion of Rhabarb, with the trochiskes of Agarick, and <hi>acetum ſquilliticum,</hi> and water of maiden haire, mixed together, which he vſed by the ſpace of ten dayes. Then was laied vpon the <hi>Scrophulae,</hi> a plaiſter of <hi>cerote magiſtrale</hi> with <hi>Cantarides:</hi> which drew forth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie of the vlcer, and great ſtore of <hi>Sames,</hi> being applied for 15. dayes together. This done, I gaue him the decoction of <hi>Salſa parilla,</hi> with a good diet, for twentie dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then I applied vnto the ſore a <hi>cerote</hi> of <hi>Gualtifredo di Medi,</hi> which in a ſhort time cured him, that had bene vexed with them foure yeares before.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                     <p>ANother which was a maide of 13. yeares of age, was vexed with <hi>Scrophulae</hi> in her throte, which was alſo in this manner cured. Firſt I gaue her the extract of <hi>Elleborus niger,</hi> with <hi>mel roſarum;</hi> which doth very effectually purge the melancholicke humor. That done, I gaue her our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe againſt the melancholick humor, for eight or ten dayes together: and applied vnto the ſores an vnguent of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>targe, boiled with the powder of <hi>Scrophularia:</hi> thus was ſhe in ſhort time cured.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another againſt Scrophulae.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcipe</hi> Verdigreee, Pelitorie of Spayne, docke roote, the iuice of leekes, of the herbe <hi>Scrophularia, ana,</hi> mixe them, and lay on lint, and applie it vnto the <hi>Scrophulae,</hi> but take ſome care thereof.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18630:37"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of Panaricium, or Panaricies, called the whit blow.</head>
                  <p>THis greeuous and intollerable maladie, (as thoſe know well that haue felt them) commeth on the end of the finger; and is an infirmitie, bred in the liuer, whereof nature being willing to diſcharge her ſelfe, ſendeth it to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme parts of the fingers: and moſt commonly it commeth to the finger next the thombe, but ſeldome in the other. The reaſon or cauſe whereof is hidden, ſaue that we may conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture (as we haue ſaid before) an accident in the liuer, which nature ſendeth forth vnto thoſe parts to eaſe her ſelfe. When it commeth to the end of the ſinger, that it can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it cauſeth a ſharpe and exceſſiue payne: and the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent comming vnto that place, not hauing paſſage, is ſo hote, that in ſhort time it putrifieth the ſinewes, muſcles, and cartilages, and in the end rotteth both fleſh and bone. The ſecret of this griefe, is not commonly knowne, of the moſt Surgeons: who with all their learning, cannot deuiſe to cure it, as it ought to be cured. The moſt part of ſuch, as haue that infirmitie, loſe their finger: but if thou wilt quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly helpe them, follow this methode.</p>
                  <p>Firſt let them bleed on the liuer veyne: then let them be well purged. Afterward dreſſe the finger, with <hi>oleum ſulfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris:</hi> which will cauſe ſome paine, neuertheleſſe (to haue ſome eaſe) you muſt abide it. The next day dreſſe it with <hi>Magno licore,</hi> vntill it be whole, which will be in ſhort time, as I haue often proued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of greeuotu vlcers, in womens breaſts.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt they muſt be touched with <hi>oleum ſulfuris:</hi> then make this vnguent. Take of the yolkes of egges, ℥ <hi>ij,</hi> turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18630:37"/>
butter, barlie flowre, honie of roſes, <hi>ana</hi> ℥ ſs: incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them all in a morter, and therewith dreſſe them, vntill they be whole. But if they come of any kinde, or ſpice of the pocks, this vnguent will be to very ſmall purpoſe. But then ſhall you dreſſe them, with our <hi>Vnguento magno:</hi> which is appropriate vnto the diſeaſe, and looke that you purge them with our <hi>Aromatico.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the diſeaſe called Aſthma, and the cure thereof.</head>
                  <p>THis diſeaſe, which is called the <hi>Ptiſicke,</hi> is a certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, contained in the lungs, which doth harden and drie them in ſuch manner, that ſuch as are troubled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, cannot fetch their breath. It proceedeth of aduſtion of the bloud, that cannot runne in the veynes: and ſo the lungs lacking ſuſtenance, worketh that effect. This diſeaſe is cured foure manner of wayes. Firſt you ſhall let them bloud vnder the toung cutting, thoſe veynes ouerthwart, and ſuck them as much as they can: for it euacuateth and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the opilation of the bloud, and eaſeth the lungs of all that euill matter which offendeth. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly you ſhall giue them a doſe of <hi>Aromatico,</hi> which euacuateth the ſtomacke, of all euill qualities, that offend the lungs. The third is, to let them eate for a moneth together, euery morning ℥ j, of our <hi>Electuario de Althea.</hi> The fourth, to annoint the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, euery night with <hi>Magno licore.</hi> But euery ten dayes, you muſt take a doſe of our <hi>Electuario Angelica,</hi> whereby thou ſhalt helpe them quickly. You muſt alſo keepe a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber diet: refraining fiſh, porke, ſlimie things, ſpice, baked meates, cheeſe and ſuch like, which nouriſh groſly, and do infect the bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18630:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> To know the Dropſie confirmed in a man the cure whereof, is ſhewed in the xxxij. Chapter of the ſecond part of the Collection.</head>
                  <p>THere are three ſignes or tokens, of a confirmed Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Firſt looke whether the toung be white and cold: then, whether the yard be ſhronke into the bellie, and laſtly if there do any veines appeare, on the bellie. If you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue theſe, they are infallible declarations of a confirmed Dropſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> An excellent remedie, againſt the Wormes.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall giue the patient <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 
                     <hi>ij,</hi> of our <hi>Vnguento magno,</hi> to drinke with <hi>Mel roſarum,</hi> three mornings together; annoint the noſethrilles therewith, and in three dayes, they will be expelled were they neuer ſo many.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the hardneſſe of the milt, and the cure thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe ſplene or milt is hardned, by reaſon of ſuperfluous humiditie, that it taketh from the liuer, and lungs. Therefore if you will helpe this infirmitie, it were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to vſe medecines abſterſiue, and drying, which thou ſhalt do thus. Firſt giue them our <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then let them vſe this Electuarie, which is of maruailous vertue in that opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Take <hi>Crocus Martis, Scolopendria, ana</hi> ℥ j, <hi>Spiknard, lapis lazuli, ana ℈ ij,</hi> Cinamon, ℥ ſs, mixe them, and make an Electuarie thereof with purified hony, and take thereof eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning one ſpoonfull, and euery night, (two houres before ſupper) an other ſpoonfull, and annoint the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18630:38"/>
part part, where the greefe is, with our <hi>Balſomo arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic.</hi> and in ſhort time, the diſeaſe ſhall be cured.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another remedie, very effectuall, for the former diſeaſe.</head>
                     <p>LEt them bloud on the two veynes, vnder the toung. That done, mixe muſtard ſeede with the vrine of a boy, and lay it betweene two clothes: and applie it to the part affected, one night, and then (if thou feele not good eaſe) vſe it agayne till the diſeaſe be gone. Alſo the decoction of oke, helpeth the ſwelling of the milt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Gonorrhaea, or running of the raynes, and the cure.</head>
                  <p>THis diſeaſe, is a corruption, cauſed of the ſuperfluous vſe of women, that are infected therewith: for ſuch men as haue knowledge of them, they receiue the ſaid corruption which afterward commeth forth of the yard, with great payne and difficultie in making water; and moreouer in the night, when that part is erected, it cauſeth great tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which for fifteen or twentie dayes, cauſeth extreme payne. This is the beginning of the French pocks, a fit ſawce for that ſweet ſinne of <hi>Lecherie.</hi> It bringeth moſt commonly payne in the interiour partes, or payne in the raynes, armes, and legges: in ſo much that in fine, it commeth to that fowle diſeaſe. For ſuch as haue this <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> neuer ſuſpecting or fearing the afterclaps, ſuffer their diſeaſe, to grow on further and further till their cure will very hardly or neuer be accompliſhed. Therefore I wiſh euery man, to ſeeke helpe in time, leaſt by letting it paſſe; in the end, it turne to his deſtruction. The cure is as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt you ſhall giue them our <hi>Aromatico,</hi> once in white wine. Then morning and euening, for ſeuen or eight dayes, vſe this potion following: annointing alſo the raynes, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18630:39"/>
thoſe parts, with our <hi>Aqua ſaetida,</hi> being cold, and in ſhort time they ſhalbe healed.</p>
                  <p>℞. the whites of ſoure or fiue new layd egges, ℥ ij of fine ſugar, ℥ <hi>iij</hi> of roſe water mixe them well, and drinke it mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening. This is a rare ſecret, and often proued, the drinke muſt be dronke cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Hemerhoides, and their cure.</head>
                  <p>THe Hemerhoides, are an alteration in the Hemerhoidall veynes, cauſed of a corrupt and putrified humor, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of nature being willing to diſcharge her ſelfe, ſendeth forth by thoſe veynes vnto the extreme or outward parts, where it cannot paſſe through, and cauſeth the alteration and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flation that is called the <hi>Hemerhoides.</hi> This corruption and putrifaction, is cauſed of the euill qualitie of the liuer, which corrupteth the bloud, and is the cauſe of all this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience. Commonly the originall and beginning thereof, is cauſed of the pocks, a thing that muſt be conſidered of in the cure. Now for the cure, it were neceſſarie to helpe the liuer, to purifie the bloud, to alter the <hi>Hemerhoides,</hi> and to diſcharge nature of that impediment. Firſt therefore, giue them our <hi>Electuario Angelica,</hi> the next day, they ſhall take our <hi>Sirupo ſolutino,</hi> whereof they ſhall take fiue or ſixe doſes. Then let them annoint the Hemerhoides, with our <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtike,</hi> once or twiſe, and they ſhall ſoone after be cured.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of the diuers ſortes, and diuers effectes of the Hemerhoides, and their cure.</head>
                     <p>BY reaſon of this diſeaſe, that commeth alwayes at the end of <hi>Inteſtino,</hi> or <hi>Longanon,</hi> ſome haue maruailous payne about the fundament, ſome burne wonderfully, and others do ſcald: which commeth, becauſe of the good or bad qualities in ſome, more then in other ſome, as experience ſheweth. For (as I ſaid) ſome haue ſuch a burning, that they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18630:39"/>
can take no reſt, ſome haue ſuch payne, as they cannot ſit, ſome haue it ſo ſcalding hote, that it is intollerable. Though this infirmitie is more hurtfull in one complexion, then in an other, and the cure hard: yet you ſhall cure them in this manner. Firſt giue them <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then purge the body fiue or ſix times, with our <hi>Sirupo ſolutiuo.</hi> Then giue him our fume at the lower parts, three or foure times, and then annoint the parts with our <hi>Balſamo artiſic.</hi> of that will drie, and take away the payne altogether, and the patient ſhall be ſurely healed.</p>
                     <p>There are diuers kinds of Hemerhoides, but two in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall. The one ſort is in the fundament, and cauſeth great payne when they go to the ſtoole. The other ſort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth of the fundament, and are not ſo paynfull as the firſt. To cure thoſe within the fundament, you ſhall giue the patient eight or ten dayes together, our <hi>Sirupo magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> warme, then let them take our <hi>Aromatico,</hi> once, and vſe cliſters, wherein is put halfe an ounce of <hi>Aqua reale Phio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauante</hi> at a time, and ſo thou ſhalt helpe them. The beſt way for thoſe that are come forth, is to make inciſion, or to make a little hole in them, that the bloud (which is putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) may come forth, and ſo by euacuation thou ſhalt helpe them. Alſo you ſhall vnderſtand, that vomiting is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in the cure of both ſortes, becauſe it openeth the veynes. Alſo <hi>Oleum ouorum,</hi> doth eaſe the payne of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merhoides very greatly: ſo doth the oyle of figges, if you annoint them therewith. ¶ The tooth of an horſefiſh bein gworne in a ring on the finger after the body is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged taketh them away by a ſecret and hidden qualitie, a thing proued more then an hundred times.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the cure of ſuch, as were troubled with ſuffocation of the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>A Certaine woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, affected therewith hauing much paine &amp; greefe, in her ſtomacke, was cured, by taking a doſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18630:40"/>
of our <hi>Electuario Angelica.</hi> Then ſhe vſed our ſirupe againſt paynes of the mother, eight or ten dayes, and annointed her ſtomacke, with <hi>Magno licore</hi> euery night.</p>
                  <p>A certaine young woman, afflicted in manner aforeſaid, wanted alſo her naturall ſickneſſe, and began to looſe her naturall heate: ſo that nature could not digeſt, the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matter in her body, was thus helped. Firſt ſhe tooke our <hi>Electuario Angelica,</hi> and euery night, annointed her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, noſethrilles, and pulſes, with <hi>Magno licore,</hi> and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning dronke of our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> and ſo was cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> To cure a rupture in the beginning.</head>
                  <p>IN euery ten dayes once, giue them our <hi>Aromatico,</hi> and euery morning faſting giue them ℥ j, of white Tartar, in water or wine; and two houres before ſupper, you ſhall take the like: Let your bread be rye, alſo you muſt weare a truſſe fit for that purpoſe, and vſe this remedie following. Take of the ſpirite of wine ℥ xij, frankincenſe <hi>Olibanum, maſtiche ſarcocolla, ana</hi> ℥ ſs, infuſe them in the ſaid <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and therewith waſh the rupture twiſe a day, then preſently caſt thereon, the powder of <hi>Biſlingua,</hi> and the herbe <hi>Balſamina,</hi> and lay thereon a cloth, wet in the ſaid water, and bind on the truſſe ſo hard, as he may poſſiblie abide it; and hereby ſhalt thou heale any great rupture in an hundred dayes, but ſee that you keepe a diet accordingly.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                     <p>TAke very ſtiffe and thicke paper well gummed, chew it in thy mouth till it be ſoft: then lay it vpon the rupture, and weare thereon a truſſe fit for the purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>Some vſe to ſteepe the paper in lye, and wring the ſame out till it be drie, and applie it to the rupture, chaunging it once in 24. houres.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18630:40"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Of retention of Vrine, and the cure thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe retention of vrine, ariſeth of many cauſes, one is grauel, that ſtoppeth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duits, where it ſhould paſſe, an other is the want or weakneſſe of the vertue expulſiue; ſo that nature cannot expell; an other is a carnoſitie, which is an alteration cauſed of corrupt and putrified humors, which do ſo reſtraine the powres, and vrine, that it cannot paſſe. There is another, and that is viſcoſitie of the reynes, ſo groſſe, that it hindreth the vrine from paſſing. Another cauſe, which is too too common, is the <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> when it chaungeth into <hi>Stranguria,</hi> that it is a ſtopping or choking of the conduites, that carrie the veyne to the bladder. All theſe foreſaid cauſes, proceede of one originall, euen of the diſtemperature of nature, whereof if you aske the reaſon, you ſhall vnderſtand, that it ariſeth of that filthy begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the French pocks. That which moueth me to beleeue it, is the obſeruation thereof diuers and ſundry times, for I haue cured many that were infected with the pockes, which were troubled, ſome with Carnoſity (before ſpoken of) ſome with grauell, ſome with debilitie of the vertue expulſiue, ſome with <hi>Gonorrhaea;</hi> all which when I had cured of the pockes: the other diſtemperatures were therewith alſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For that diſeaſe, is the cauſe of twentie miſchiefes, and the reaſon, why many Phiſitians, make a long cure of the former diſtemperatures, is for that they know not the mayne and principall cauſe of them. But now I will ſhew thee a true and excellent manner of curing the retention of vrine, which way ſoeuer it commeth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt giue them a doſe of <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then giue vnto them our <hi>Syrupo ſolutiuo,</hi> eight or ten dayes, but in any wiſe keepe no ſtraight diet, but a good gouernement as you do moſt commonly vſe: and eate ſuch meate as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thy ſtomacke beſt: cauſe them alſo to ſweate, and in ſhort time, thou ſhalt thoroughly cure them.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18630:41"/>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:18630:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18630:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18630:43"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> A moſt excellent remedie to cure the difficultie of vrine.</head>
                  <p>THe difficultie or retentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vrine, cauſed diuers wayes, as of grauell, viſcoſitie, exulceration, &amp;c. is in this ſort very well and ſafely cured. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe of this difficultie of vrine, is in the reynes or kidneies; ſo that it be not a ſtone in the kidneies: or ſome great ſtore of grauell, ſee that thou worke thus.</p>
                  <p>℞. <hi>Rognoni</hi> of a male hare, boile it in good wine, when it is well boiled, ſtampe it ſmall, and paſſe it thorough a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with the ſaid liquor wherein it was boiled. Remember that when you boile it, there muſt not remaine much liquor in the veſſell. Then take the ſaid matter, that you ſtrained, and put thereto as much purified honie, and boyle it on a ſoft fire, vntill it come to the forme of an Electuarie. When it is boiled, put thereunto, for euerie pound of that Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, theſe things following, made into fine powder, of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum aloes,</hi> of Cinamon, <hi>ana</hi> ℈ j, cloues, ſaffron, <hi>ana</hi> ℈ j, muske, graines foure, <hi>Aquae roſarum</hi> ℥ j, our <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> ℥ i ſs. Incorporate theſe well together, while it is warme, and keepe it in a glaſſe, cloſe ſtopped. And when you will vſe it, you muſt firſt take a doſe of our <hi>Electuario Angelica,</hi> and while you vſe the Electuarie, remember to annoint the reynes, with our <hi>Aqua faetida,</hi> when you go to bed. Of the Electuarie you muſt take ℥ j, in the morning, and faſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on foure houres, and vſe ſome exerciſe, and in ſhort time, thou ſhalt ſee a maruailous good worke performed. For the reynes will be ſtrengthned, the viſcoſitie will be reſolued, the powres will be opened, and the vrine will be expelled, and clenſed, all which are effectes, neceſſarie for him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, that will with honeſtie and credite, helpe the former maladie.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another often proued.</head>
                     <p>If thou wilt preſently helpe one, that cannot make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18630:43"/>
by reaſon of wind, viſcoſitie, or other greeuous cauſe, vexing the partie: annoint their reynes, and all the priuie partes, with our <hi>Balſamo Artificiato,</hi> and keepe them verie warme, and forthwith they ſhall make water, to their great ſatisfaction.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Retention of the Vrine, with ſtitch in the ſide.</head>
                     <p>ONe was in verie ſhort time cured of theſe infirmities, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had taken our <hi>Aromatico:</hi> and annointed him, in manner aboue ſpecified, with our <hi>Balſamo Artificiato.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The ſwelling of the legge, and foote, cured in manner following.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt the patient tooke one doſe of <hi>Aromatico,</hi> then he vſed our <hi>Quintaeſſence ſolutiue,</hi> three or foure mornings together, in a little broth. That done, he dronke euerie morning, a little of our <hi>Quintaeſſence vegetabile,</hi> faſting, and euerie night, he annointed his legge, with <hi>Oleum Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum noſtrum.</hi> Alſo now and then he tooke a doſe of <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulae Angelica,</hi> to keepe the body ſoluble, he kept a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable good diet, he vſed not much walking, ſo that verie ſhortly after he was well cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of Chilblaines and their cures.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand, that Chilblaines (as we terme them) are cauſed of no other thing, then of humors dried, and reſtrained in our bodies. For in the winter, when it is cold, the pores do ſhut ſo cloſe together, that the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor cannot paſſe, or come forth, neither by ſweat, nor other exhalation or expiration. For that cauſe, the humors in a young man (who is hote of complexion) may not be kept in; for then nature (which would eaſe her ſelfe) ſendeth that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18630:44"/>
exhalation, vnto the extreme parts of the bodie, that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the handes and feete; where remaining there is cauſed that alteration: and in proceſſe of time, the skinne doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the humor goeth forth; but cannot heale, till the ſpring, when warme weather commeth in. Howbeit I haue found out a ſecret to cure them quicklie, and with great eaſe. Firſt let them bloud, then giue them a doſe of our <hi>Electuario Angelica:</hi> after that let them take our <hi>Syrupo ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuo,</hi> ſix or ſeuen dayes together not keeping any ſtraight diet or rule. After this annoint them with <hi>Oleum philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum de cera &amp; terebinthina,</hi> at night when they go to bed: and do thus one weeke at the leaſt, and then no doubt thou ſhalt cure them as I haue often proued. Alſo the oyle and water of franckinſence, will do the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of Cornes on the feete, and the manner to take them away.</head>
                  <p>THe cornes that come on the feete, are a kinde of hard tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, or thicke excreſcence, cauſed of corrupt and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied humors, whereof nature being willing to diſcharge her ſelfe, ſendeth them to the lower part of the feete, whereout becauſe they cannot paſſe, there do they make reſidence: ingendring that kinde of tough excreſcence, which is gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and painfull. Many times, the cauſe hereof, ariſeth of that noyſome diſeaſe, <hi>Morbus Gallicus,</hi> as ſome write, and then muſt it be remedied with medicamentes appropriate thereunto. But if they come otherwiſe, then to take them away follow this order. When they are in their, greateſt ſtate, and cauſe moſt payne, cut them vntill they bleed, then annoint them with our <hi>Balſamo Artificiato</hi> applying it ſo hote, as you may ſuffer it; thereupon go to bed. Then touch them once or twiſe with <hi>Oleum ſulfuris,</hi> and annoint them with <hi>Oleum Philoſophorum de terebinthina &amp; cera,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be whole.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:18630:44"/>Some take the iuice of <hi>Semperuiuum,</hi> and annoint the cornes therewith. Then they take wormwood, and lay it vpon an hote tile ſtone, and ſprinkle it with ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and being hote, bind it vpon the Cornes, and in three or foure times ſo doing (as I haue bene crediblie certified) the Cornes will be taken away.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of an infirmitie that commeth on the fingers ends, and in the feete, vnder the nayles, and the cure of it.</head>
                  <p>MAny men are greatlie troubled herewith, and in ſuch manner, as thereby they are made altogether vnfit to go. It commeth on the great toe, vnder the naile, or the ſide of the nayle: for the moſt part, and a man would thinke, that the nayle grew in the fleſh, but it is not ſo, for the fleſh groweth vpon the nayle, though this infirmitie appeare not, to be a thing of great importance (whereof the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue made little mention) yet is it a thing greatly to be regarded. For many great perſonages, that liue eaſily, and are tormented with the gout, haue alſo this greefe in thoſe parts: but the order to cure them is this. Firſt you ſhall cut the nayle, on that part where it moſt greeueth them; then take it away which you may do eaſily, without any great payne to the patient: for the nayle is already ſeparated from the greeued place. Thus when the nayle is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, touch it with our <hi>Cauſticke,</hi> whereof mention is made in our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the plague. Let it ſo remaine three dayes together: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dreſſe it euery day, with <hi>Magno licore,</hi> vntill it be whole, which will be in a very ſhort time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of Eriſipela, and the cure thereof.</head>
                  <p>THis diſeaſe (as experience ſheweth) is cauſed of an hote and fierie moiſture, ariſing in the face, armes and legges;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18630:45"/>
for where it is, the powers and pores are ſtopped, that the ſaid moiſture, cannot haue expiration, whereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth tumor: as alſo a ſhutting &amp; cloſing vp of thoſe pores, by meanes of the ordinarie annointing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with fats, oyles, &amp;c. or other cold things: a common courſe vſed of common Surgeons. Againſt this there cannot be found a more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy, then the ſpirite of wine, or <hi>Aqua ardens,</hi> or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing it with hote water: and if you waſh the parts affected with our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> the powres will be opened, and it penetrateth and aſſubtilateth that humiditie, cauſing it to come forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note>Alſo you ſhall finde, that by drinking our <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> and annointing the ſtomacke with <hi>Oleumcerae,</hi> diuers are cured of a certaine heate, retained in the ſtomacke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The cure of Wartes.</head>
                  <p>THere is an herbe, called in the Italian toung <hi>Herba di vento:</hi> in the iuice whereof, if you wet a cloth, and bind it vpon the wartes, they will weare away in ſhort tune after.</p>
                  <trailer>The end of the firſt part of the Appendix.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18630:45"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE APPENDIX OR ADDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, VNTO THIS COLLECTION, contayning the vſe and vertues, of ſundry vegetables, animals, &amp;c. gathered out of the Phiſickes, of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Leonardo Phiorauante.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the vſe and vertues, of Ebulus or Danewort.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the buds of this vegetable, when they are young and greene,<note place="margin">To purge flegme.</note> perboile them in water, and make thereof a ſallade, and giue it vnto thoſe, that haue coſtiue bodies, and it will prouoke them to the ſtoole.<note place="margin">Strengthen the ſinewes.</note> It is an herbe, verie profitable for the ſinewes, it comforteth the weake partes, and preſerueth ſuch, as are weake in the ioints from many accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: it purgeth flegme, which (for the moſt part) cauſeth debilitie of the nerues. Whoſoeuer vſeth to drinke of a ſirupe, made of the berries thereof, ſhall not be troubled with the gowt, nor any diſeaſe.<note place="margin">
                        <p>Preuent the gowte.</p>
                        <p>The generall vſe.</p>
                     </note> in the articular partes. The ſeede dried, is profitable, againſt all infirmities cauſed of humiditie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Elleborus niger, and the vſe thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe roote of blacke Hellebore,<note place="margin">To purge me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie.</note> being dried and kept two yeares, may be ſafely vſed, without other prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and may be miniſtred againſt any infirmitie, that hath his originall, of a melancholicke cauſe. Therefore it is moſt appropriate, againſt the feuer quartaine, and lunatike per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18630:46"/>
vexed with melancholie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the vſe and vertues of the herbe called Gratia Dei, a kinde of Geranium in Engliſh blew Storkes bill.</head>
                  <p>TAke of <hi>Gratia Dei,</hi> dried in the ſhadow, and beaten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſine powder, ℥ j, Cinamon <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, cloues, ℈ j, wheate flowre, <abbr>lb</abbr> j, orenges condite, ℥ j, make thereof a paſt, with honie, and bake it in the ouen with bread: but take great heed,<note place="margin">Cure of Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulae.</note> that it burne not. Of this you ſhall giue ℥ j, to purge againſt many infirmities: but aboue the reſt againſt <hi>Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phulae,</hi> againſt ſcabs, and the white ſcall. For it euacuateth onely the ſuperfluous humiditie of the body, it drieth and is appropriate for ſuch kinde of infirmities.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Howbeit you muſt note, that all ſoluble medecines are not fit, for one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe or complexion: for chiefly and properly, Rubarb pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth choller, blacke Hellebore auoideth mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cholie, Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort diſpoſſeſſeth the body of flegme, and this herbe clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the bloud.<note place="margin">One medicine may worke vpon diuers cauſes.</note> Therefore euery one hath his peculiar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie: though ſometime either of them, may worke, vpon more cauſes then one, yet not ſo properly or ſimply, but by accident, and in regard of circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Prouoke vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite.</note>Two drammes of the powder of this herbe, dronke in wine, or broth, prouoketh vomite and ſiege, and is very good for ſuch as are lunatike.<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> It helpeth or at the leaſt delayeth the extremitie of the feuer. It is good againſt greefes of the ſtomacke, and wind in the bellie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Putrified vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note>A decoction thereof made with ley, helpeth putrified vlcers, if they be waſhed therewith: for as it purgeth the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, ſo it clenſeth the ſore, and healeth it quicklie, if you wet a cloth, in the ſaid ley, and applie it thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of Rubarb, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>THe herbe called, in the Italian toung, <hi>Lappacia maggiore,</hi> or <hi>Rombice domeſtice,</hi> is a kinde of Rubarb, which among
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18630:46"/>
the learned Herbariſtes is termed by the name of <hi>Rhare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiorum:</hi> whereof <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, when it is new will loſe the bodie, euacuate choller, as the <hi>Rhabarbarum</hi> doth.<note place="margin">Purge choller.</note> It is very good againſt oppilations: it purgeth the bloud, and taketh away ſcabs.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall haue,<note place="margin">The correction or vſe.</note> a moſt precious medecine thereof: if you mixe the greene roote, with honie, cinamon, ſaffron, gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the powder of roſes.</p>
                  <p>If you roſt the roote in the embers,<note place="margin">Scrophulae.</note> and mixe it with condited ſugar it breaketh the <hi>Scrophulae,</hi> and mundifieth them, and healeth them in ſhort time. Some do mixe it with the gumme, called <hi>Ammoniacum;</hi> and ſo do bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the forme of an vnguent, and applie it vnto the parts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with <hi>Scrophulae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Tithymale, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>GAther the herbe Tithymale (called Spurge) in the moneth of May: take forth the iuice and mixe it with ſugar roſet, or ſugar violet, in fine powder:<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> then make of them both a moiſt paſt, and keepe it in a glaſſe, cloſe ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
                  <p>When you purpoſe to vſe it, miniſter two ſcruples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in broth or any other conuenient ſirupe. It purgeth without payne, helpeth al feuers that come of heat:<note place="margin">Feuers.</note> working not onely by the ſtoole, but prouoking ſweat alſo.</p>
                  <p>It reſolueth all continuall and quotidian feuers,<note place="margin">Greeuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</note> when the parties affected therewith be hote, and their ſweat cold, yea though they be brought very low, it will by Gods helpe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them of their troubleſome aduerſarie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laureola</hi> doth alſo moue the body, by vomite and ſiege,<note place="margin">Note.</note> but it may not be vſed in any continuall feuer or quotidian; becauſe it will inflame too much.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:18630:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Soldanella, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>THis herbe groweth, in ſandie and ſalt ground, and is hote and drie.<note place="margin">Dropſie.</note> It purgeth by vomite and ſiege, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt the dropſie, all windineſſe, and vnwholeſome moiſture in the bodie. Being taken in lozenges, with <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matico,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Purge ill moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</note> the quantitie of <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, it ſendeth forth all the noiſome waterineſſe, out of the bodie, drying and heating thoſe parts, in an excellent manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII</hi> Of Cyperus, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Paſsions or windie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>THe herbe <hi>Cyperus,</hi> called in Engliſh Galingall, being put into new wine, giueth it an excellent good taſt, and ſmell, preuailing againſt inward paſſions, cauſed of wind. It is good for ſuch as are burſten, for it reſolueth the wind: if you take the powder thereof being ſtamped very ſmall, and make a plaiſter thereof,<note place="margin">Rapture.</note> with other things appropriate ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, applying the ſame to the rupture, and chaunging it once euery day. Alſo if the patient do once in a day eate of the roote, he ſhall in ſhort ſpace be holpen of that diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Elder, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>TAke the rootes of Elder, waſh them cleane, and ſcrape them till you come to the wood, ſtampe that ſubſtance, and take the iuice, and ſtraine it, boile it, &amp; ſcumme it well, and for euery ℥ of the iuice,<note place="margin">Coole the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke purge the bloud.</note> take one ℥ of <hi>Mel roſarum,</hi> and drinke it, for it will coole the ſtomacke, helpe hote feuers quickly, and purge the bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the vertues and vſe of Tabaco.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The uſe.</note>TAke of the greene herbe and roote <abbr>lb</abbr> iij ſs ſtampe it in a morter with a little ſalt, then put it in a glaſſe with ℥ vj.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18630:47"/>
of the ſpirite of wine, and ſet it thirtie dayes to putrifie in horſe doung. Then diſtill it in <hi>Balneo,</hi> till all the ſubſtance be come forth: and put therein as much <hi>Oleum ſulfuris</hi> as will make it tart. Then keepe it cloſe, and giue thereof eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning a ſpoonfull, to any one affected with the feuer,<note place="margin">Feuer.</note> and it will helpe him in ſhort time.</p>
                  <p>If any man be affected, or greatly troubled with vlcers or ſcabs: let him drinke thereof euery day one ſpoonfull,<note place="margin">Vlcers.</note> and waſh the ſores therewith, and in ſhort time it will moſt wonderfully cure them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of ſweet Margerom, and his vertues.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſweet Margerom, and ſtampe it, and take of the iuice, ℥ j. oyle of bitter almonds <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, and ℈ j of Maſticke, and ſnuffe it vp at the noſe, three or foure mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and annoint the head with oyle of egges. This purgeth the head, of all paynes, diſſolueth tumors,<note place="margin">Payne in the head.</note> quickneth the ſight, and prouoketh ſleepe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Perſicaria, his vſe and vertues.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand, that this herbe, doth worke (in a manner) againſt all infirmities, moſt ſtraungely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. For if you take the powder thereof, and put it vpon copper molten, it will in the proiection, become like gold, and will draw it to a ſmall quantitie, and make it malleable,<note place="margin">The chimicall vſe.</note> and ſoft like gold, except the colour.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if you make a ſtrong ley of the aſhes of <hi>Perſicaria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Another chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall vſe.</note> and therein boile yellow brimſtone, it will draw out of it quicke ſiluer, which is the Philoſophers Mercurie. This herbe doth alſo moſt notablie preſerue a man from many infirmities, if one part thereof be taken whiles it is dry, and our other part of <hi>Specie venetiane;</hi> being both of them well
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18630:48"/>
incorporate together, and vſed in your meates.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of man, and the medecines that are made of him.</head>
                  <p>MAn is a rationall, or reaſonable creature, whereof we haue written at large in our booke called <hi>Phiſica del Fiorauante.</hi> But here we will onely write of certaine mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, that may be made or deriued from him: which are for the eaſe, helpe and remedie of diuers infirmities which are in men and women. The reaſon whereof is very good, for euery like reioyceth with, and helpeth his like, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man ſerueth for man.<note place="margin">
                        <p>The nature and qualitie of the partes of man.</p>
                        <p>The fat.</p>
                        <p>The bloud.</p>
                     </note> The fat of a man is (as euery man knoweth) hote, and penetratiue, and mollifying if you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the parts therewith, (where the ſinewes be hard) and drawen together, or contracted, therefore it will quicklie reſolue them. I haue made the <hi>Quintaeſſence</hi> of mans bloud, rectified and circulated, with the which I haue done moſt wonderfull cures, for if you giue thereof <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, it will reſtore thoſe, that lye at the point of death.</p>
                  <p>It is moſt profitable, againſt thoſe infirmities that are in the bloud: for it correcteth the malignitie of the bloud, and preſerueth it, as well as the ſpirite of wine. If you put a litle of it into an hogges head of wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">Purifie wine.</note> it will purifie it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it a long time: more then any other thing whatſoeuer. So that this <hi>Quintaeſſence,</hi> worketh more effectes, for the cure of great and dangerous infirmities then any other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The liuer of a man.</note>Alſo from the liuer of a man, will be drawen by diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a water and an oile. If the water be dronke euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together, by the ſpace of a moneth, in the quantitie of <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j, with ℥ ij of liuerwort water, it will recouer ſuch as are halfe rotten thorow diſeaſes of the liuer, and hath diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther properties, whereof I will not ſpeake at this time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fleſh of man.</note>From the fleſh of man diſtilled, there will come forth a ſtinking water, and an oyle, which is moſt excellent, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18630:48"/>
woundes withall, when they are badly healed, and that there remaine any hurt about thoſe parts, that they are out ſo ſenſible and pliant, (as they were wont to be before) this reſolueth them. And it mollifieth and ſoftneth all hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of any tumor, of what originall ſoeuer it ſhall come.</p>
                  <p>From the forepart of a mans ſcull,<note place="margin">Manſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll.</note> there is drawen by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, a water and oyle, and a ſalt, which is moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably vſed, againſt the falling ſickneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Finallie, from ech other part of man, there are medecines to be made, for the cure of ſundry diſeaſes in man, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as you may alſo read, more at large, in the ſpagiricke preparations of <hi>Ioſephus Quercetanus</hi> publiſhed in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh by <hi>Iohn Heſter</hi> Practitioner in the Spagiricall art.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of an henne, and the Phiſicall vſe thereof.</head>
                  <p>SOme write, that the fleſh of an henne, will diſſolue gold, and that the bones will calcine it eaſily.</p>
                  <p>Another told me, that the aſhes of hennes fethers,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lue and calcine gold.</note> being calcined white, doth mundifie, incarnate and cicatriſe vlcers.</p>
                  <p>Alſo there is made,<note place="margin">A reſtoratiue.</note> an excellent reſtoratiue of an henne, after this manner.</p>
                  <p>Take a good fat henne, and pull her quicke, and take forth the guttes onely, and ſtampe her in a morter. Then boile it, in xij, <abbr>lb</abbr> of faire water, with ℥ j of ſalt, till <abbr>lb</abbr> viij be conſumed. That done, paſſe it thorow a ſtrainer, and diſtill it in <hi>Balneo,</hi> till all the ſubſtance be come forth. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you may giue, vnto the ſicke at all times, with a little of a plaine and ſimple Iulepe. When you finde any euill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, in the bellie, you muſt adde thereunto, a little oyle of ſweet almondes, newly made, (while it is warme) for then is it one of the beſt reſtoratiues, that can be found out or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed in the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:18630:49"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Of Eeles, and the medicinall vſe them.</head>
                  <p>MAny haue vſed, the fat of an eele, againſt deafeneſſe, but to ſmall purpoſe. But if you will diſtill the eeles, with <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Againſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> you ſhall haue a moſt ſubtill oyle, which doth moſt excellently preuayle, againſt that infirmitie.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if you boile the skinnes of the eeles, in ſtrong ley vntill they be diſſolued, then ſtrayne it and boile it to a thickneſſe: and it will be a moſt ſtrong glew for wood or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther workes.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if you annoint a corroding vlcer therewith it will greatly repreſſe the rage thereof and comfort it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the Barbill, and to what vſe ſhe ſerueth in medecine.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Loſe the bellie.</note>IN the moneth of May the Barbill hath egges, which are of a ſoluble quality, and of ſome thoſe egges being eaten; they ſhall be prouoked to vomite.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The vſe and qualitie.</note>They haue a qualitie contrarie to other purgers they muſt be dried in the ſunne, mixed with a little <hi>Sena,</hi> and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſtred in wine or water that is ſodden. When it hath well wrought, the patients muſt eate good meate to nouriſh them, and may drinke wine, and (when they are diſpoſed thereto) ſuffer them to ſleepe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of Bees, and their medecinall vſe.</head>
                  <p>BEes are of nature hote and moiſt, hauing a generatiue propertie.<note place="margin">
                        <p>Sterelitie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented.</p>
                        <p>To quicken dead bees.</p>
                     </note> For if they be giuen to any barren creature they ſhall conceaue in ſhort time after.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if yon lay dead bees in a drie place to putrifie, wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them ſometime with wine, they will reuiue agayne,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18630:49"/>
though not as they were before, but they will be much big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and of an other forme.</p>
                  <p>Theſe bees if you bring into powder with as much Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarides; boile them a little with oyle of Chamomill,<note place="margin">Cauſe haire to grow.</note> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint any part where the haire is fallen away, and it ſhall quickly come agayne, and in a ſhort ſpace, a moſt ſtraunge thing to behold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of frogges, and their vſe.</head>
                  <p>THe skinnes of frogges being boiled and made into the forme of a plaiſter with waxe and franckincenſe,<note place="margin">Hote afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable for ſuch as haue any maligne or troubleſome accident about their legges thorow heate.</p>
                  <p>The fat of frogges is a wonderfull medecine againſt <hi>Fuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ſacro,</hi> or <hi>S. Anthonies</hi> fire,<note place="margin">S. Anthonies fire.</note> a diſeaſe hapning vnto children and others through the great heate that is in their bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of Centumpedes, called in Engliſh, Sowes.</head>
                  <p>IF you miniſter the powder of theſe creatures in wine, it hath many excellent properties, but chiefly,<note place="margin">Stitch in the ſide.</note> it hath bene experienced, greatly to preuayle, againſt the ſtitch in the ſide, for it will helpe that greefe preſently.</p>
                  <p>If you burne the little crieking creature, called a Cricket, and miniſter the powder thereof, in ſome <hi>Diureticke liquor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prouoke vrine.</note> it prouoketh vrine.</p>
                  <p>Mallowes, <hi>Alkakengi, Centum nodi, Centumgrana,</hi> and the rootes of Rapes: are of like propertie, being handled and vſed according to art.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are oftentimes found in ſtanding pooles, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified waters, certaine ſmall creatures, which are rounde like a cherry, hauing a tayle and two feete, which are in Lombardie called <hi>Comazz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Take theſe, and diſtill there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18630:50"/>
of a water or liquor,<note place="margin">Diſolue Iron.</note> wherewith you may very ſoone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume or breake iron: a very great ſecret obſerued in nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of the reſine or gumme, called Tacca Mahacca, and the vſe thereof.</head>
                  <p>TAke thereof as much as you will, diſtill it in a retort of glaſſe, &amp; from it there will come both oyle and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Of which I haue ſeene diuers medecines made, againſt ſundrie diſeaſes. Annoint the bellie, with this oyle cold, when you go to bed:<note place="margin">Cruditie of the Matrix.</note> and it helpeth againſt the cruditie of the Matrix.</p>
                  <p>If the genitall part of the man be annointed therewith before the act of generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Helpe concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the woman ſhall be the more fit for conception: for by this meanes ſome kinde of ſterilitie is taken away.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Payne in the head.</note>It helpeth and eaſeth payne in the head, proceeding of a a cold ſtomacke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Helpe dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note>It helpeth digeſtion, and reſolueth payne, throughout the body, in what part ſoeuer, they ſhall come: ſpecially, when they haue their beginning of cold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Wind in the ſtomacke.</note>The water hereof, diſſolueth wind in the ſtomacke, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth digeſtion, prouoketh vrine, mitigateth all feuers that come of cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of the gumme Carrana, and the medecinall properties of it.</head>
                  <p>TAke it, and diſtill it in a retort with the yolkes and whites of egges, and there will come forth oile, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the oyle whereof will be blacke, and the water red.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chilblaines.</note>The water of <hi>Carranna</hi> helpeth Chilblaines, and all choppes or clefts in the lippes ariſing of cold in the winter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Sore breaſts.</note>It is a great eaſe, for the ſore breaſtes of women, that giue ſucke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:18630:50"/>The oyle worketh wonderfull effects,<note place="margin">Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> in woundes of the head, arme, or legges.</p>
                  <p>Annoint a ſimple wound therewith, once or twiſe:<note place="margin">Heale quickly.</note> and it will very ſpeedily be healed.</p>
                  <p>Take a quantitie of this gumme, and mixe it with as much of the ſeede of water creſſes, and the white of an egge, and make thereof a cerote, to apply vnto a rupture:<note place="margin">Rupture.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it will in ſhort time be healed, all other circumſtances being alſo obſerued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of liquide Amber, and the medecinall vertues thereof.</head>
                  <p>TAke liquide amber, and diſtill it in a retort: and from thence, there will come a red oyle.</p>
                  <p>This oyle is vſed, againſt all indiſpoſitions of cold,<note place="margin">Cold and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe.</note> and moiſture, or wind.</p>
                  <p>The ſame healeth ſcabs, and is good for woundes.<note place="margin">Scabs.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you annoint the ſtomacke therewith,<note place="margin">Comfort the ſtomacke.</note> it will excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly comfort the ſame: for it is a thing vncorruptible, and like vnto <hi>Balſamum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Appendix vnto the former Collection.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
